<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Enchiridion legum a discourse concerning the beginnings, nature, difference, progress and use of laws in general, and in particular, of the common &amp; municipal laws of England.</title>
            <title>Enchiridion legum.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39391</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E720</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22664</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12061864</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12061864</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53249</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39391)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53249)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 66:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Enchiridion legum a discourse concerning the beginnings, nature, difference, progress and use of laws in general, and in particular, of the common &amp; municipal laws of England.</title>
                  <title>Enchiridion legum.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 140 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Elizabeth Flesher [and 4 others], and are tobe sold by G.S. [and 14 others],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Customary law --  England --  London.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53249:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53249:1"/>
            <p>Enchiridion Legum: <hi>A DISCOURSE CONCERNING The Beginnings, Nature, Difference, Progreſs and Uſe, OF</hi> LAWS in GENERAL; <hi>And in Particular, OF THE</hi> Common <hi>&amp;</hi> Municipal LAWS of ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by <hi>Elizabeth Fleſher, Iohn Strea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and <hi>Henry Twyford,</hi> Aſſigns of <hi>Richard Atkins</hi> &amp; <hi>Edw. Atkins,</hi> Eſquires.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And are to be ſold by</hi> G. S. H. T. J. P. W. P. J. B. T. B. R. P. C. W. T. D. W. J. C. H. J. L. J. A. J. W. <hi>&amp;</hi> J. P. <hi>M DC LXX III.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53249:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:53249:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE HEADS Of the ſeveral</hi> CHAPTERS <hi>Conteined in this TREATISE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>CHAP. I. THE Definition, Etymologie, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, Perfection and Imperfection of Laws: What is required to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of them, and of their neceſſity.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 1.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>CHAP. II. The differences betwixt the Làws of Nature, of Nations, the Civil and Municipal Laws.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 16.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>CHAP. III. Of the grounds of the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:53249:3"/> and how they do differ from other Laws.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 31.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>CHAP. IV. An anſwer to certain Objections uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally made againſt the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 57.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>CHAP. V. Of the Books written of the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> whereby the Knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is Chiefly obtained.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 83.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>CHAP. VI. Of Eſtates allowed by the Law of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 89.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>CHAP. VII. Of Aſſurances &amp; Conveyances which grow out of theſe Eſtates by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-law.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 95.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>CHAP. VIII. Of Actions and of their Trials accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:53249:3"/> to the Common-laws of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 103.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>CHAP. IX. Of Trials allowed by the Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 106.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>CHAP. X. Of ſome things in the Miniſters and proceedings of our Laws conceived worthy to be reformed.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 111.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:53249:4"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53249:4"/>
            <head>Enchiridion Legum.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 1. <hi>The definition, etymologie, diviſion, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and imperfection of Laws: What is required to the making of them, and of their neceſſity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MEaning to treat firſt of Laws in general, and next of the Common or Municipal Laws of this Kingdom; I conceive it cannot be unprofitable for an Introduction un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this intendment, to ſet down the definition of a Law: whereof <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> hath delivered three, derived out of <hi>Demoſthenes, Chryſippus,</hi> and <hi>Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One is, that a Law is ſaid to be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that, whereunto men ought to yield obedience, as in other reſpects, ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in this: becauſe it is an inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53249:5"/> of the Gods, a decree of Wiſe men, a correction of offences committed, either wittingly or ignorantly, a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of the whole Commonwealth with one accord, after the direction whereof every Citizen ought to order his life. The other is, that the Law <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> is ſaid to be a Soveraign of all things, both <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane:</hi> That is, a Commander, a Guide, and a Square both of good and bad, enjoyning that which is fit, and forbidding the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. The one of theſe, is rather a deſcription, than a definition; and it deſcribeth rather the Natural, than the Poſitive Law: And the other is fitting rather to an Orator, than a Lawyer. We may therefore let them paſs, and proceed to the third; which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſetteth down the Law, to be a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral determination of Wiſe men, a Comptroller of Faults either eſcaped through ignorance, or committed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wilfulneſs: And it is a general agreement of the Commonwealth. <hi>Jaſon</hi> obſerveth, that the Law is a general Commandment in three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects: either becauſe it is founded upon a general Authority; or becauſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53249:5"/> it belongeth to, and bindeth all; or elſe becauſe it is intended general for the profit of all. <hi>Cicero</hi> defineth the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Law to be a certain reaſon flowing from the Divine mind, which doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade that which is right, and prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit the contrary. And <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith, that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> the Law obtaineth a name like to the name of the mind. But whilſt the Law is defined by the Divine mind, it ſeemeth (as one ſaith) to be defined by that which is more remote and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, than ſubject to common capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Yet are theſe definitions in ſome ſort true, being rather referred to the eternal Law, than to the poſitive and humane Laws, as ſhall be ſhortly ſhewed in his place. In the mean time, for that theſe (as the former) are, as was ſaid before, rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions than perfect definitions; to come more near to the purpoſe: It may be ſaid, that humane Law is an <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Order and Ordinance including the Rule and Reaſon of Governing, and giving to every man, that which is his due; directing to the end of publique good, determining puniſhment to the Tranſgreſſors, and reward to the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53249:6"/> Therefore to conclude; humane <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Laws are nothing elſe but the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and agreement of Wiſe men, concluded by publick Authority for the peace and profit of the greater part of the people living together in ſociety. It is ſaid [for the greater part] be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no humane poſitive Law is ſo generally good unto all, but that it is hurtful unto ſome, by accident if not of it ſelf.</p>
               <p>If any do deſire to know from <note place="margin">The deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word <hi>Lex,</hi> which we call Law.</note> whence this word <hi>Lex</hi> (which in Engliſh we call Law) is derived: Some will ſay with <hi>Iſidorus,</hi> that it hath his etymologie, <hi>à legendo;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> after the Law was written, it was wont to be read unto the people. But this is not ſo certain, in that the reading of the Law by way of promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation was but accidentary, and no eſſential part of the Law; although ſome have endeavoured to prove, that a Law could not be perfectly eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed until it were promulgated by way of Proclamation.</p>
               <p>Others will derive the word <hi>Lex,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>à ligando;</hi> for as much as Divines hold, that men are tyed in <hi>foro conſcientiae,</hi> to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53249:6"/> the obſervation of the Laws, as well as they are bound under penalty to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſame: Yet <hi>Cicero</hi> concurreth with the firſt derivation, (but with a farther-fetch'd reaſon than the former) <hi>quod Lex idem ſit, quod legendi, hoc eſt eligendi regula;</hi> the reaſon is, <hi>nam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula dirigendo, docet eligere.</hi> It may yet well enough agree unto both, for one ſaith, <hi>Habet Lex quod ſit Regula, &amp; quod ſit obligatoria praeceptio.</hi> How ſoever theſe derivations of the word <hi>Lex,</hi> do ſtand falſe or true, it makes not much matter, ſo we leave them as more Grammatical and Conjectural, than certain and infallible.</p>
               <p>The word <hi>Lex,</hi> which in Engliſh we <note place="margin">A double ſignification of this word Law.</note> call Law, hath in our language a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſignification, or is taken two ways; for it is taken both for that which the Latines term <hi>Lex,</hi> and for that which they call <hi>Juris prudentia;</hi> the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Art of the other: For <hi>Lex</hi> is the rule, and meaſure of things to be done, and to be left undone; but <hi>Juris prudentia,</hi> is the knowledge and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of that rule: as Juſtice is the Execution of them both, which hath his force in giving to every man that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53249:7"/> which is his in <hi>praemio, paena, &amp; debito.</hi> So then in the firſt ſence the word Law is properly applyed; but in the ſecond, it is ſomewhat largely extended; yet uſe and common opinion hath ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted it.</p>
               <p>This Law hath for his ſubject and object the Rule of all Divine and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane things, (except God himſelf) who is the great Rule-giver and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker; and he being <hi>Liberum agens,</hi> is ſubject to no Law; but his own Will is the perfect Law of Juſtice, which is the Fountain from whence all Laws are derived, to all things in Heaven and in Earth.</p>
               <p>Law hath a threefold reſpect, and is divided according to the diverſity of things to which this great Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver doth diſpenſe Law: They are of three kinds, to wit, the Natural, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and Reaſonable agents. To the firſt are referred the Elements, and all compounded things without life: They are guided by that Law which was impoſed on them at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and they do never break it. The ſecond, which is the Senſible agents, are all living Beaſts, which are guided
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53249:7"/> not with ſo forcible a Law of neceſſity as the firſt; for they are not ordained to keep their certain and ſetled ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but they do follow their own kind and appetite: wherein yet they do not tranſgreſs the Laws of Nature. The third kind of agents, called Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, are Men and Angels, and they at firſt were created with a poſſibility of performing or not performing the Laws impoſed on them.</p>
               <p>According to theſe three forenamed <note place="margin">A threefold Law.</note> Subjects of Law, there is a threefold Law (as ſome ſay) given unto them; that is, the <hi>Divine, Natural,</hi> and <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane:</hi> The firſt delivered by God, and written by the direction of his Holy Spirit in the Old and New Teſtament. The ſecond, ſtamped and as it were engraved by him in mens hearts. The third, derived out of the two firſt; and deviſed for Government and Society amongſt men.</p>
               <p>Some others do divide Laws into four parts, that is, the Law of <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> or the eternal Law of God, which is his wiſdom, by which from Eternity he that is called <hi>Antiquus die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> hath pre-ordained all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53249:8"/> their beginning, whereof St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, when he ſaith, that <hi>Deus vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eat ea quae non ſunt, tanquam ea quae ſunt.</hi> The ſecond is, the <hi>Divine</hi> Law <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which God hath given in his Old and New Teſtament, to conduct men unto their ſupernatural end, for his Glory and Service, and for their own final Salvation. Of this <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſpeaketh by the Spirit, and as in the Perſon of God, <hi>Dabo Legem meam, in viſceribus eorum ſcribam eam.</hi> Of the third, which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is the <hi>Natural</hi> Law, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> maketh mention, <hi>Gentes quae legem non habent, naturaliter quae legis ſunt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt.</hi> Of the fourth, which is the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>Humane</hi> Law, (warranted by Gods Word) the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe ſpeaketh; <hi>Omnis anima poteſtatibus ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limioribus ſubdita a ſit:</hi> So that all theſe Laws have their warrant from Gods Word; ſave the Eternal Law, which was his will and wiſdom, being from the beginning before any Law was written, or could be divulged.</p>
               <p>Therefore next to the Eternal Law, <note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the Divine Law.</note> the Divine Law ſpringing from the ſame, hath his place and preheminence, before all other in Dignity and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53249:8"/> becauſe from it all other good Laws have their derivation and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, or elſe are ſquared by it; and for that it ſuffereth no mutation in it ſelf: In amplitude, becauſe it afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſelf-ſame Rules and meaſure to all Men, and Nations, without diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Perſons, Place, and Time, or any other ſuch like circumſtances by which other Laws are often altered. And of this Divine Law, the Decalogue or Ten Commandments, delivered by God unto <hi>Moſes</hi> on the Mount, and by him to Gods people, is a Compendium, or full Epitome of all the reſt; as unto which the reſt may be reduced, as Concluſions drawn out of certain Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</p>
               <p>The Law Divine delivered by God <note place="margin">The Law of <hi>Moſes, or of the Old Teſtament, more antient than any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Law.</hi>
                  </note> unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> is in Antiquity before all Humane Laws: for though <hi>Pliny</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about to prove, that <hi>Ceres</hi> was the firſt gave Laws unto men, and as others attribute that honour unto <hi>Radaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus;</hi> yet <hi>Joſephus</hi> writing againſt <hi>Apion,</hi> directly proveth, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was the firſt did promulgate unto men, the Laws delivered unto him from God, and that long before thoſe Law-givers,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53249:9"/> whom <hi>Iſidorus</hi> nameth, as <hi>Pharonius</hi> to the <hi>Grecians, Mercurius Triſmegiſtus</hi> to the <hi>Aegyptians, Solon</hi> to the <hi>Athenians, Lycurgus</hi> to the <hi>Lacedemonians, Numa Pompil.</hi> to the <hi>Romans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Law of Nature, is next to the <note place="margin">The Law of Nature next to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Law.</note> Divine Law, in excellency, antiquity, immutability, and ſeverity: becauſe it began with mans Creation, it never changeth, being nothing elſe (as one defineth it) according to the part of the Law of Nature which is called ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condary, (whereof we ſhall have cauſe to ſpeak ſomewhat in the next Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) but, <hi>dictamen rationis in rationabili creatura;</hi> therefore this Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſecondary, is the effect of Gods Law in the mind of man, and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion thereof; as a ſtep in duſt, is the effect of the foot which firſt framed it: And this ſecondary Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is in ſome ſort contrary to that firſt Law, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth the Law of the Members, being a natural inclination to ſenſuality.</p>
               <p>After theſe Laws followeth the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane or Poſitive Laws of men, which being the preſcript and particular rules by which the actions of men ſhould be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53249:9"/> reduced and conducted to their due ends, and this grounded on the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, Divine, and Natural Laws, (men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before) but yet ſtill meaſured, and moulded by the reaſon, invention, and diſpoſition of men, which is moſt commonly variable and diverſe; no marvel then, if alſo the Laws of men (ſetled upon ſuch ſlippery foundation of different reaſons and affections) be alſo changeable, and ſubject to imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; whereof <hi>Juſtinian</hi> in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the <hi>Digeſts,</hi> doth render the like reaſon: ſaith he, <hi>Sed quia divinae res quidem perfectiſſimae ſunt; humani vero juris conditio ſemper in infinitum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currit, &amp; nihil eſt in eo, quod ſtare poſſit perpetuo: multas enim formas natura no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vas edere deproperat.</hi> No Humane Laws can be made abſolutely perfect, no more than other Arts and Sciences can be perfected by men; ſince Art is the imitator of Nature, and even Nature her ſelf is imperfect in her works. The concluſion therefore is ſhort, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; That thoſe Humane Laws tend moſt (although hardly can they attain) to perfection, which do ſquare moſt, and moſt depend on the Divine, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53249:10"/> and Natural Laws. And on the contrary, thoſe poſitive Laws of men, are moſt corrupt and unprofitable, which ſwerve moſt from them.</p>
               <p>Since we ſee what Laws are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteſt, and which are ſubject to moſt imperfection, let us a little conſider what conditions are required in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws to help them towards per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: They by <hi>Iſidorus</hi> are deſcribed to be theſe; that is, that they be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, <note place="margin">Certain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to bring Laws towards per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</note> juſt, poſſible, according to nature and cuſtom, convenient and agreeable to the time and place; that they be neceſſary and profitable, manifeſt and perſpicuous, (leſt by their obſcurity the uncircumſpect be intrapped) that they be not made for private profit, but for publick utility: Others require fewer (yet as effectual) qualities in Laws, that is, to contain honeſty, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, poſſibility, conveniency; for the end of Humane Laws is, that by the dread of their puniſhment innocency may be ſafe in the midſt of wicked men.</p>
               <p>There are alſo certain habilities re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite <note place="margin">Certain ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for Law-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</note> in thoſe who are Law-makers, amongſt which the School-men do
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53249:10"/> chiefly eſteem theſe three parts or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tential faculties of prudence, <hi>Ebulia, Syneſis, Providentia:</hi> The firſt is, the faculty of Counſelling, and adviſing aright: The ſecond is, the habit of judging ſoundly, (not ſo much the Caſes of Law already made, as the Conſiderations of Laws to be made:) The laſt, which is Providence, being a fore-ſight of future events; this hath two parts, Circumſpection, and Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: the one being the conſideration of Circumſtances, leſt any thing be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective in the proviſion of the Law; the other ſearcheth into the Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities and Inconveniences whereto ſuch Laws (or they for whoſe ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard it is made) may be expoſed.</p>
               <p>The Philoſopher requireth to the <note place="margin">What the Philoſopher requireth in making of Laws.</note> making of good Laws, Authority, Reaſon, general Juſtice, which is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, and Agreement of the People. By the firſt the Law-maker doth bind, by the ſecond he doth know, by the third he doth deſire to make ſuch Laws as ſhall be poſſible, and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, not for himſelf only, or for a few, but for all, or at the leaſt the greateſt number; for <hi>Suprema Lex, Salus Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli.</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:53249:11"/> The notions, and general rules of Nature do teach to ſhun that which is hurtful; but where the Naturaliſt or Moraliſt doth not perſwade, the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician and Law-maker doth enforce. The Moraliſt doth indeed preſcribe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rules, and Precepts what ought to be done: But doth not ſhew ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, how it ſhould be done. The Rules of good and evil preſcribed by Nature, and ſet down by the Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, are by them both enjoyned to be practiſed, by and to our ſelves; but by the Politician, and Law-giver, thoſe general Rules are applyed and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated to the particular Laws of each Nation, to be faſhioned not only for our ſelves, but for others. Therefore it is aptly ſaid, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Ethicus deſinit, ibi incipit Juriſperitus;</hi> as in Nature, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi phyſicus definit, incipit medicus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though theſe poſitive and politick <note place="margin">The neceſſity and utility of Laws.</note> Laws of Men cannot attain to abſolute perfection, yet that they are of evident utility and urgent neceſſity, I ſuppoſe no man doubteth. For both nature and neceſſity (the two raiſers of Sciences and Invention) have as it were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired to direct, and require the uſe of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53249:11"/> theſe Humane Laws; becauſe as it is natural unto men to deſire and to like that which is others, and yet to diſlike and abhorr other men; from whence come queſtions, controverſies, quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, oppoſition, and defence: ſo out of theſe doth ariſe an inevitable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, to lay certain limits (which are Laws and Civil Conſtitutions) by which theſe inordinate deſires, and deſigns of men (being full of diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance) ſhould be bounded; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, as the appetites and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men are reſtleſs, and of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unreſtrained; ſo except they were confined and reſtrained by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Laws, the lawleſs wills of men would make ſociety uncomfortable and unſafe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:53249:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The differences betwixt the Laws of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of Nations, the Civil and Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Laws.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving ſaid ſomewhat of the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and nature of Laws, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the Eternal, Divine, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Law) it now followeth, that we ſhould deſcend to diſcover the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences betwixt the Humane Laws of ſeveral ſorts. Theſe, by ſome, are divided into three branches, (from whence it is ſuppoſed that all other particular poſitive Laws do ſpring and grow:) The firſt is the Law Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, (whereof there hath been a little ſpoken before) this is defined, to be that which Nature hath taught all living Creatures: The ſecond is the Law of Nations, which is received amongſt all Countries and People: The laſt is the Civil Law, which every free Commonwealth ordaineth for it ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53249:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caius,</hi> a Civil Lawyer, divideth <note place="margin">A diviſion of Laws into two parts.</note> theſe Laws but in two parts; that is, the Natural, and Civil Law: for ſome think, that whatſoever Law is Natural, the ſame is alſo the Law of Nations; and ſo on the other ſide interchangeably. The reaſon is thus; What elſe is the Law of Nations, <note place="margin">A queſtion concerning the former diviſion.</note> but that which natural Reaſon hath taught and perſwaded all men, to be equally good for all? So that it is called National, or the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, becauſe all Countries have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it: Natural, becauſe it had its beginning from natural Reaſon.</p>
               <p>For the deciding of which doubt, <note place="margin">The Law of Nature two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</note> it is to be underſtood, that the Law of Nature is twofold, <hi>Primary,</hi> and <hi>Secondary;</hi> the one being that which Nature (or rather the God of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) teacheth all living Creatures; the other, that which Nature teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Men. The firſt, called the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of Nature; whereby it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all living Creatures, by the inſtinct of Nature, to procreate, and to ſeek the preſervation of their own kind; to avoid that which they find to preſent death and danger; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53249:13"/> force with force; to ſeek things needful for ſuſtenance, and the like. This in a general ſence, is called <hi>Jus primaevum,</hi> or the primary Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: And this doth differ from the Law of Nations, which is a Law pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per only unto Men, and not to other Creatures. But the Secondary Law of Nature, or of God, (for both is one and the ſame) containeth and comprehendeth the Precepts of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, which God and Nature hath infuſed into Mans heart, at his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; given only unto Mankind, and unto him from his beginning; as, to yield Religious reverence to the Supreme and Divine power, to exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite love and duty towards our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and the like. This latter part of the Law of Nature, doth anſwer and concurr with ſome part of the Law of Nations, which likewiſe (as the former) is twofold, that is to <note place="margin">The Law of Nations twofold.</note> ſay, Primary, and Secondary. The Primary Law of Nations is that which natural Reaſon hath inſigned all Nations, (as hath been expreſſed in the Secondary Law of Nature) therefore ſome have termed the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condary
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53249:13"/> Law of Nature, the antient Law of Nations. But there is a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condary Law of Nations, which is no part of the Primary or Secondary Law of Nature; this cometh not by nature, but by a Judgment gathered out of experience and diſcourſe, thereby collecting what is commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious for common ſociety, and equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behoofeful to all Nations; and this is not ingraffed in nature at firſt, but gotten and gathered by uſe and neceſſity, which makes thereof a Law: as, to puniſh offenders and wrong-doers, which is the firſt head of the Secondary Law of Nature, yet not a Rule or Law begotten or bred by Nature. But when the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe nature of Man could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it ſelf in temperancy, then wrongs offered, publick neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, that they ſhould be puniſhed who would hurt others, and trouble the common peace and ſociety of Men; leſt the like occaſion of wrong doing ſhould grow general, and ſo in the end hurtful to all: So by this Secondary Law of Nations, grew the diviſion of Goods, the diſtinction of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53249:14"/> Properties, free Commerce betwixt Nations, common Contracts, and the like. By this we ſee, that the Secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary <note place="margin">The ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary Law of Nations no part of the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> Law of Nations is no part of the Law of Nature, and differing alſo from the Primary Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions it ſelf. Now let us ſee next, how the Civil Law differeth or is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from theſe Laws of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and of Nations.</p>
               <p>The Civil Law (or the appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">The name of the Civil Law taken two wayes.</note> thereof) is taken in two ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſignifications; for either it is in a ſtrict ſignification, accounted parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly and only for the <hi>Roman</hi> Law, firſt ſet down by <hi>Papirius, Papinian, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian,</hi> and others, and afterwards collected into the Inſtitutes, Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dects, or Digeſts, Novels Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Feuda, by <hi>Juſtinian</hi>'s commandment: or elſe in a more proper ſence, it is accepted for the particular Laws which every King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Commonwealth doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute for it ſelf. And although <hi>Caius,</hi> with other learned Civilians, do confeſs, that the Laws which every City doth make for it ſelf, be properly intituled <hi>Jus Civile, quaſi jus</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:53249:14"/> 
                  <hi>proprium ipſius Civitatis;</hi> yet the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> having gotten under their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection the greateſt part of the known World, gave Laws unto all Nations Conquered by them, which by a kind of Excellency they termed <hi>Jus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum,</hi> or <hi>Jus Civitatis.</hi> Therefore <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> after he had cauſed the Digeſts to be compiled, commanded his Judges, that theſe Laws ſhould be uſed in all Countries; and that his Pretors of the Eaſt, of <hi>Illyria, Lybia,</hi> and other parts, ſhould put them in practice: Whereby it came to paſs, that the <hi>Roman</hi> or Imperial Laws were generally called the Civil Laws, and have for the moſt part (in moſt places) been ever ſince ſo obſerved. Whereas otherwiſe, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſence and ſignification, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Laws of each free City and State, ought to be called their Civil Laws. But both theſe, that is, the <hi>Roman</hi> and Imperial Civil Laws, and <note place="margin">The Civil and Munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Laws do not wholly differ from, or depend on the Laws of Nature and Nations.</note> the particular Civil or Municipal Laws of every City, Commonweal, or free State, do not wholly differ from the Laws of Nature and of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, nor wholly depend on them;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53249:15"/> in this, becauſe the Laws of Nature and of Nations are permanent and perpetual, being alwayes the ſame without any alteration: But the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that is to ſay, the <hi>Roman</hi> Civil Laws, have been ſubject to many <note place="margin">The <hi>Roman</hi> Laws ſubject to ſundry mutations.</note> mutations, alterations, and abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: So likewiſe all other Civil and Municipal Laws, have been, and are, according to the variation of Times, of States, and of ſundry cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances.</p>
               <p>For example, in the <hi>Roman</hi> Laws, <note place="margin">The Laws of the Kings of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </note> whilſt the <hi>Roman</hi> State was under the Government of Kings, they made ſuch Laws as they thought fit for that time, the preſent ſtate of the City, and their own purpoſes, which were all digeſted into one Volume by <hi>Sextus Papirius,</hi> (as is recorded by <hi>Pomponius:)</hi> But the force of theſe Laws ended with their Reign; and as ſoon as the Commonwealth was tranſported into a New State, at the firſt they could not frame any certain or conſtant Laws; for the Commons and Gentry oppoſing each other for <note place="margin">The Laws of the Conſuls and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </note> twenty years together, ſuch Laws as were then made, did rather ſeem to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53249:15"/> croſs and contend one with the other, than to concurr in any mutual harmony for the good of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth. For the Conſuls made Laws according to the minds of the Senate, and the Tribunes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple according to their affections; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they agreed to ſend certain Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates unto <hi>Athens,</hi> and other Cities of <hi>Greece,</hi> (famous at that time for good Laws and Government) that they might be better pleaſed with Foreign Laws, who envied and held not their own indifferent: Which done, they drew thoſe Laws brought <note place="margin">The Laws of the 12 Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles fetch'd from <hi>Greece</hi> to <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </note> from thence into Ten Tables, to which they added two more of their own; theſe they called the Twelve Tables, (being the grounds of the <hi>Roman</hi> Laws:) But yet two years after theſe Laws were brought to <hi>Rome,</hi> and eſtabliſhed there, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the <hi>Decemviri</hi> (upon which the force of theſe Laws did depend) ceaſed and was extinguiſhed, by the luſt and licentious life of <hi>Appius Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius,</hi> being one of them. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thoſe Laws of the Twelve Tables, continued afterwards as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53249:16"/> grounds of other Laws, yet were they ſtill added to, and altered as the <hi>Roman</hi> State did change. For when <note place="margin">The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of <hi>Rome</hi> make and change Laws at their pleaſure.</note> the Emperors ſet up their Soveraign and ſupreme Authority, they made ſuch Laws, Edicts, and Conſtitutions, as were anſwerable to their own ends, the ſucceeding Emperor often diſannulling what his predeceſſor had ordained. And as they abrogated the Laws of others, ſo did they not long uphold their own; For who almoſt was there amongſt them, that did not change their own Conſtitutions? Beſides, as the ſtate of the Empire <note place="margin">The admix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Laws in the City of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </note> grew greater, they were forced to alter their Laws, with admixture of their Decrees of the Senate, Statutes of the Commons, Ordinances of the Magiſtrates. As the Pretorian Laws (called <hi>Jus honorarium)</hi> which were of great force for the time, but of no long continuance; for they were founded upon the Authority of the Pretors, and did often end with their years. Thus the <hi>Roman</hi> Laws re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in much uncertainty, till the Reign of <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperor, who with conſent of the Senate, did cauſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53249:16"/> theſe Laws to be made perpetual; whence grew the name of <hi>Edictum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Adrian</hi>'s <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuum</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed.</note> 
                  <hi>perpetuum.</hi> But yet in divers ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ages, ſundry of theſe Laws were alſo abrogated; and even the Laws compiled in the Pandects and Codes, by <hi>Juſtinian</hi>'s commandment, were ſome of them by him altered, and many taken away in a latter Book called the <hi>Authenticks.</hi> All which is alledged to ſhew the inſtability, change and uncertainty of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Laws. The like might be ſaid of the Laws of other Nations, which have been found uncertain in their grounds, and unſtable in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance.</p>
               <p>Secondly, We may ſee that there is difference betwixt the Civil <hi>Roman</hi> Laws, and the Municipal Laws of other States: For though the <hi>Roman</hi> Imperial (called the Civil Laws) do bear much ſway in moſt Countries of Chriſtendom, and have place in <note place="margin">All Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries have ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Laws and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the Civil <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Laws.</note> their proceedings of Juſtice, (but leaſt of any place within this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England)</hi> yet have all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries their ſeveral Cuſtoms, Statutes, and particular Ordinances, diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53249:17"/> in divers points from the Rules of the <hi>Roman</hi> Imperial Civil Laws: which is no marvel, ſince in the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts</hi> there is delivered as from <hi>Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> ſome diſtinction betwixt the <hi>Roman</hi> Civil Laws, and the Preto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Laws made in the ſame City; For it is ſaid there, that the Civil Laws did conſiſt of the Statutes of the People, the Ordinances of the Senate, and Decrees of the Princes, with the Authority of Wiſe men: But the Pretorian Laws were thoſe, which the Pretors did introduce to ſupply, to help, or to correct the Civil Law. So is there alledged in the ſame <hi>Digeſts</hi> (out of <hi>Paulus)</hi> another diviſion of Laws: The firſt is the Law of Nature, the ſecond is the Civil Law; the firſt is freed from Injuſtice, the ſecond is deemed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to all, or the greateſt part of the City; and there is added, <hi>Jus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The Preto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Law differing from, and correcting the Civil Law.</note> 
                  <hi>honorarium,</hi> or the Pretorian Law, as if it were no part of the Civil Law; wherein it is ſaid, the Pretor doth give Law, though he doth determine unjuſtly; having relation not unto that which the Pretor doth, but to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53249:17"/> that which is convenient for him to do. So that it is not to be wondered, that the Municipal Laws of every Country, do differ from the Civil or <hi>Roman</hi> Law; or that the Civil <hi>Roman</hi> Law hath not his full force in all Countries, or that it is not the only Law that governeth in any Country: Becauſe the City of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, did admit ſome other Law to be adminiſtred within the City, than that which was called and accounted their own Civil Law, or <hi>Jus Civile.</hi> And where there was queſtion made before, concerning the Civil Law, whether the ſame were only the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Laws, or as well other Munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Laws? Some Civilians do diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh <note place="margin">A diviſion of the Civil Law.</note> them into two parts; the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Laws they call, <hi>Jus Civile com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune;</hi> and the other, <hi>Jus Civile par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulare:</hi> To the firſt they referr alſo ſome Municipal Laws, eſpecially thoſe Conſtitutions of the Empire, ſince it was tranſlated to <hi>Germany,</hi> as the <hi>Aurea Bulla</hi> of <hi>Charles</hi> the 4th. Alſo the Conſtitutions and Edicts of <note place="margin">The Munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal or Civil Laws of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</hi>
                  </note> the <hi>German</hi> Emperors, in their Diets or Parliaments, which are reckoned
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53249:18"/> and referred to the common Civil Laws, becauſe they are ordained by Authority of the Emperor; and yet they are in true conſtruction but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Civil or Municipal Laws, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they bind none but ſuch as are ſubject to the Empire, or to thoſe places of the Empire for which they are made, and which do ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thereto.</p>
               <p>So hath the Kingdom of <hi>France</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Laws of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </note> certain particular Civil or Municipal Laws, made in their Parliaments, (which were anciently the Councils of their Kings:) but when the Kings of <hi>France</hi> did ſeparate their Councils of State from thoſe Parliaments, yet the Parliaments have been held in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Cities of <hi>France,</hi> (as ſaith <hi>Briſon</hi> Preſident of the Parliament of <hi>Paris)</hi> at certain times of the year; The firſt and principal held at <hi>Paris,</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by <hi>Philip the Fair,</hi> or as ſome ſay by <hi>Lewis Huttin</hi> his Son; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond at <hi>Tholoſe,</hi> for <hi>Languedoe;</hi> the third at <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> for <hi>Aquitain;</hi> the fourth at <hi>Grenoble,</hi> for <hi>Daulphine;</hi> the fifth at <hi>Dijon,</hi> for <hi>Burgoigne;</hi> the ſixth at <hi>Rouen,</hi> for <hi>Normandy;</hi> the ſeventh
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53249:18"/> at <hi>Aix,</hi> for <hi>Provence;</hi> the eighth for <hi>Bretaign,</hi> inſtituted by <hi>Henry</hi> the 2d. <hi>Anno</hi> 1553.</p>
               <p>They have alſo Municipal and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <note place="margin">The Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Laws of <hi>Spain.</hi>
                  </note> Civil Laws ordained for the Kingdom of <hi>Spain,</hi> as thoſe ſet down by <hi>Alphonſus</hi> the 9th. And the like for that and other Countries are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant and in uſe.</p>
               <p>The Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath (as <note place="margin">The Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Laws of <hi>Scotland</hi> and of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together different.</note> this Realm of <hi>England)</hi> ſeveral and particular Municipal Laws, differing from the <hi>Roman</hi> Civil Laws: As for the Laws of <hi>Scotland,</hi> they are not ſo far different from the Laws of this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> as divers do conceive; and that the Laws of <hi>Scotland</hi> are not altogether unlike theſe of <hi>England,</hi> (but in many points do concurr with them) is not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable: For that there is a Book, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <note place="margin">The Law Book of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia Majeſtas</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> like to <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi>'s Book of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Laws.</note> the antient Laws of that Kingdom, termed <hi>Regia Majeſtas;</hi> which, as ſome Students (having read the ſame) do affirm, (and as it is ſet forth in the Printers Epiſtle to <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi>'s Book) do agree much, and in many places word for word with the ſaid <hi>Glanvil</hi>'s Book, and doth often
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53249:19"/> vouch him: So that it is ſuppoſed the antient Laws of both theſe Realms did then agree, and do yet in moſt points; which have not been altered by Statute ſince in either of theſe Realms. Alſo King <hi>James</hi> in one of his Speeches (made to the Knights and Burgeſſes of the lower Houſe of Parliament) did pronounce and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that the Tryal in the Chancery of <hi>Scotland,</hi> was brought from this of <hi>England,</hi> ſhewing the time, Author, and occaſion thereof. Therefore it <note place="margin">An opinion that the Laws of both theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, may in main points be conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently made all one.</note> may be conceived, that there is not ſuch great diſcrepancy or contrariety betwixt the Laws of both theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; but that by due examination it will be found, that there is, or at leaſt may be, a conſonance betwixt them in many, if not in moſt points. But for the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> how they do differ from the Civil and other Laws, ſhall be ſhewed in the next enſuing Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:53249:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the grounds of the Laws of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and how they do differ from other Laws.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OUr Laws of <hi>England</hi> do differ, as in name, ſo in divers other circumſtances, conſiderations and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, from the Laws of other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Commonweals.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for the name; they receive a common appellation of the Common Laws of <hi>England;</hi> a name ſcarce given to the Laws of any other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <note place="margin">Why our Laws are called the Common Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note> Therefore whence it received this denomination of the Common Law, may breed ſome queſtion. Some ſay, that it is called the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Law, to diſtinguiſh it from the Laws of particular Cuſtoms, or of Cuſtoms allowed for lawful within this Realm: But this is not certain, nor ſcarce probable; as ſhall be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed anon, when it ſhall be demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that theſe Cuſtoms allowed for Law, are rather made parts, than
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53249:20"/> diſtinguiſhed from the Common Law. Some others ſuppoſe, that it is called <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the Common Law of this Kingdom, to make difference betwixt it and the Statute Laws; which as they are of another kind of conſtitution than is the Common Law, (as will be made evident) ſo are they of ſeveral ſorts in themſelves; as ſome of theſe Statutes are general, and ordained for all the Subjects; ſome are parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and made for the ſettling of particular mens Eſtates, and of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Trades, Corporations, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties: Therefore theſe cannot be (nor may not be called) the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Laws of the Kingdom, (that is, common to all) but only in this ſence, becauſe they are conſtituted with the common conſent of all. The third opinion is, that they are called the Common Laws of the Kingdom, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> becauſe all the Subjects of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom muſt live under them, and may challenge them as their Birth-right, for the defence of their Eſtate, Right, and Liberty. In which ſence alſo the general Laws of any Kingdom or Commonwealth may be called their Common Law.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:53249:20"/>
               <p>Howſoever it may be a queſtion, how at the firſt the name of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law came, or how the ſame may differ from the Statute Laws, or from any other Law allowed within this Kingdom; Yet it is certain that the <note place="margin">The munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Laws of <hi>England</hi> is the moſt proper Title of our Laws.</note> Term and title of the municipal Laws of this land, is both proper to our Laws and doth include all our Laws, as well the Statute as Common Law. Firſt, it is proper in that our Laws of this land are peculiar to this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and the territories thereof (and thereto adjacent) being not elſewhere in uſe or allowed. Now for the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicipal Laws of this Kingdom (under which title the ſpecial and particular kindes of our Laws of <hi>England</hi> may <note place="margin">The diviſion of our Laws of <hi>England</hi> into ſeveral parts and grounds.</note> be moſt aptlie comprehended) ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry perſons have made ſeveral Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions thereof: Some have divided them into Cuſtomes, which is like to the <hi>Civilians Jus privatum,</hi> and into Statute Law; others into Common Law, Cuſtomes and Statute Law; This laſt Diviſion conſiſting of three <note place="margin">Another di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of the grounds and parts of the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </note> parts <hi>Seingerman</hi> (in his fundamental partition of our Laws) doubleth, by adding thereto another foundation
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53249:21"/> and diviſion of our Laws, which is the Law of God, the Law of Reaſon, and certain principles or maximes which (with the three former) he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth as ſeveral grounds of our Laws of <hi>England.</hi> They which ſtand to the firſt bipartite diviſion of our Laws, (ſetting them to ſtand only as it were upon two leggs) do conjoyn Cuſtom with our Common Law; for they ſay, what is any Cuſtom allowed by the Laws of the land but the Common Law of the land? ſince that the Judges (to whom delegation is made for the <note place="margin">Whether Cuſtoms al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for lawful be ground, or made parts of our Law.</note> determination of civil Cauſes) do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thoſe Cuſtoms to be pleaded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and do give judgment for the ſame: yet the difference between them will be; firſt, that theſe Cuſtoms do not equally extend throughout the Realm, and therefore if they be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated into our Laws, they are but private, and not our Common Laws: Secondly the <hi>Judges</hi> do <hi>ex officio</hi> take notice of the one, but not without a ſpecial pleading of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: So it may well be ſaid in ſome ſort that Cuſtomes allowed for Laws, or for lawful, may be made ſome part
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53249:21"/> of our Laws, but yet I can hardly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them the honour, to be made grounds of our Laws, unleſs they be firſt reduced to certainties, and ſo be made as it were <hi>maximes.</hi> So are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral received opinions by Cuſtom, continuance, and approbation of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Judgment, made Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Laws; whereto ſome add this rule, <hi>Communis error facit Legem.</hi> As for the other addition of St. <hi>Germans</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">St. <hi>Germans</hi> diviſion of the grounds of our Laws not allowed.</note> 
                  <hi>ſextuple</hi> diviſion of our Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> although he hath therein ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome learning (yet without offence be it ſpoken) he hath muſtered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther divers things different in name, but the ſame in nature. For what is the Law of reaſon, other than the Law of God (if it be rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood) becauſe what proceedeth from reaſon (not darkned with the clouds of error,) but ſuch things as were <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ractered</hi> in the ſoul by him, which firſt framed it, according to his likeneſs? And ſaith <hi>Seneca, quid eſt ratio?</hi> he anſwereth himſelf, <hi>naturae imitatio.</hi> Therefore that our Laws of <hi>England</hi> are compoſed and wholly framed on the Laws of God is more than may be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53249:22"/> ſaid of them, or of any other humane poſitive laws; but that they do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on them, and not mainly differ from them may be well and truly ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified.</p>
               <p>Now for as much as there hath bene mention made of three principal parts of our municipal Laws, let us a little take ſome particular and ſeveral view of them what they are: they are ſaid to be the Common Law, the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute <note place="margin">The particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar parts of our Law ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined.</note> Law, and Cuſtoms allowed for law.</p>
               <p>The firſt, which is the Common Law of this land, conſiſteth partly of the collection of ſuch laws as were allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by King <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour, <note place="margin">What Laws King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> the Conqueror allowed in England.</note> who neither wholly introduced his <hi>Norman Laws,</hi> nor altogether allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the former, but out of the beſt parts of either, took that which was fitteſt for the time, and preſent go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. The former laws which he allowed of, were ſuch of the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Daniſh</hi> laws, as he found fitteſt for the time.</p>
               <p>And firſt of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> who came into this Kingdom about <hi>Anno</hi> 449. whoſe King <hi>Ethelbert</hi> of <hi>Kent</hi> did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53249:22"/> (as <hi>Beda</hi> ſaith) <hi>decreta judicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Some part of the <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Daniſh</hi> Laws allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Conqueror.</note> 
                  <hi>cum conſilio ſapientum, quae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripta</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Anglorum ſermone, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctenus habentur &amp; obſervantur.</hi> The ſucceeding <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings did in their <hi>Wintenagemotes</hi> or <hi>conventus ſapientum</hi> (which were in the nature of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments)</hi> make diverſe conſtitutions <hi>cum conſilio ſapientum &amp; ſenatorum, cum Epiſcopis;</hi> as that Learned and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious gentleman Mr. <hi>Lambert</hi> affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, who compiled ſome of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one book, as the Laws of <hi>Inas, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred, Athelſtan, Atheldred, Canutus, Edgar, Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; out of which the Conqueror took ſuch as he thought convenient, whereof ſome are enumerated by the forenamed Mr. <hi>Lambert,</hi> and by <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veden.</hi> Alſo <hi>Gervaſius Tilburienſis,</hi> he <note place="margin">The Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the former Laws.</note> ſaith of the Conqueror: <hi>decrevit ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum ſibi populum viri ſcripto, legibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſubjicere: propoſitis igitur Legibus Anglicanis, ſecundum tripartitam ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum diſtinctionem, hoc eſt Merchenleg, Daneleg, &amp; Weſt Saxenleg; quaſdam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probavit, quaſdam autem approbans,</hi> &amp;c. <note place="margin">The firſt part of the Common Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </note> So then we ſee that King <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror took ſome of the ancient
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53249:23"/> Laws of this land, which is the firſt part of our Common Law of <hi>England.</hi> The reſidue which came for a ſupply unto the ſame, ſprang out of the judgments given ſince in particular caſes upon arguments made before, and by the learned <hi>Judges</hi> of this Land.</p>
               <p>The ſecond part of the Municipal <note place="margin">The ſtatute law dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from the Common Law, yet a part of our Municipal Laws.</note> Laws of this land (though not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called but differing from the Common Law, as the <hi>Pretorian</hi> Law amongſt the <hi>Romans</hi> did differ from their Civil Law) is the ſtatute Law of this Realm, made by the King as head, with the Nobles and Commons, as members of this body politique.</p>
               <p>This Law was invented to give ſpeedy remedy and redreſs unto ſuch ſuddain matters as were miſchievous in the Commonwealth, the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and prevention whereof was defective, diſpuniſhable, or not fully provided for, by the Common Law; the firſt of which ſtatute Laws now extant was made in the nineth year <note place="margin">The firſt ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute law that is now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant.</note> of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third. For the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Statutes and aſſembling of Parliaments (in which they were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained)
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53249:23"/> he which will diligently read the ancient Stories of <hi>Malmesbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Huntingdon, Hoveden,</hi> and <hi>Math. Pariſienſis</hi> (eſpecially above others) ſhall find that there are no ſmal miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings in ſome things about the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity and true conceipt of their Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms and ſtrength.</p>
               <p>There is (according to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome) another part of our Law (or at the leaſt, a derivative out of the ſame) that is, the Cuſtoms held for Law, or judged lawful, which have been allowed of ancient times <note place="margin">Cuſtom laws, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of our Laws as ſome hold it.</note> in particular Counties and places of this Kingdom, as in <hi>Kent</hi> they have many, and eſpecially that of <hi>Gavel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind</hi> throughout the whole Country, whereby as well the youngeſt as the eldeſt Son ſhould equally inherit, which they reſerved and retained by offering battel to King <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror. The Cuſtom of Borough Engliſh is another, whereby the younger Son is only inheritable, and this is particular to ſome ancient Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs, and peculiar only unto them. There is likewiſe the Cuſtom of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> Honour, containing many privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53249:24"/> particular to that place. So have diverſe other great Lordſhips, Mannors and ſome Corporations their particular Cuſtoms and ſpecial privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, which are therefore properly called priviledges, <hi>quaſi privatae leges;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">How privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Laws.</note> and theſe having by long Cuſtom and conſent had continuance and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, they are thereby made lawful, and in ſome ſort ſtiled and reckoned as part of our Laws, although in ſome points they do differ from the rules of the Common Law. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Civillians</hi> call ſuch Cuſtoms, <hi>jus ſingulare, quod contra tenorem ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis propter aliquam utilitatem, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate conſtituentium introductum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Laws of <hi>England</hi> do dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the Laws of other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, there is no doubt; as there is no Country but hath ſome conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions contrary to any other even of their neighbour Countries Laws.</p>
               <p>But if any do demand how the <note place="margin">Wherein the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> do dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Laws.</note> Laws of <hi>England</hi> do differ from other Laws, it may be found ſomewhat in their inſtitution and foundation, more in their form and method, but moſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53249:24"/> in the courſe of their proceedings and execution.</p>
               <p>For the firſt it is apparent that the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Laws of other Countries (for the moſt part) are grounded, or do fetch their Rules from the <hi>Roman</hi> and Imperial <note place="margin">The Laws of <hi>England</hi> take not their grounds from the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil <hi>Roman</hi> laws as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther laws do.</note> Civil Law, but the Laws of <hi>England</hi> are not founded, nor do any way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, on the Civil or <hi>Roman</hi> Imperial Laws. For the Laws of <hi>England</hi> take their grounds from the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Rules of reaſon, equity and general reſpects: weighing therewith what is convenient or inconvenient to the whole Commonwealth, or the greateſt part thereof, and holding it for a general Rule to be ſafer and better to ſuffer a miſchief than an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience.</p>
               <p>The ſecond difference betwixt the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Inſtitution of our Laws and the Laws of other Countries is, becauſe the Laws of this Kingdom are not made <note place="margin">The <hi>Prince</hi> doth not of himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone make the Laws of England as the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Princes</hi> have done.</note> by the <hi>Prince</hi> only, as ſometimes the Laws of the Empire and of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places were, where the <hi>Princes</hi> had both an affirmative and <hi>a Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power</hi> in ordaining Laws for the people under them. But in <hi>England,</hi> as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53249:25"/> the Laws concerning penalties in Criminal cauſes, or in Civil, cannot be enacted and eſtabliſhed without the Kings Royal approbation: So doth not the King make theſe Laws without the conſent of his <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Laws of <hi>England</hi> do likewiſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> differ from the Laws of other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, firſt becauſe the Common Law of <hi>England</hi> is not all written and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſet down; but doth reſt much <note place="margin">The Law of <hi>England</hi> not all writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten nor all ſet down in Method.</note> as ſome ſay in <hi>Pectore Judicis;</hi> and alſo it doth differ in Method from the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Law and from ſome other Laws, becauſe it is not digeſted into Method by Titles, Chapters and diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For the firſt, though it were to be wiſhed that the Common Law were all written, and that it were ſo made certain (if that might be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) as it ſhould not need to depend upon private and particular opinions; yet if that may not be, the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience is not altogether ſo great, as ſome conceive it: for all Countries <note place="margin">Some coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries had their Laws written, and ſome had not.</note> have not had their Laws written and ſet down alike: The <hi>Athenians</hi> uſed only written Laws: The <hi>Lacedemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:53249:25"/> had none written: The <hi>Romans</hi> had both.</p>
               <p>The laſt difference betwixt the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Law of <hi>England</hi> and other Laws, but eſpecially the Civil Law, being in the proceedings and execution thereof, which will appear principally in theſe three parts; Firſt, in the manner of <note place="margin">Three diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Laws of <hi>England</hi> and the Civil Laws.</note> Summoning (as we ſay) or Citation (as the <hi>Civilians</hi> call it.) Secondly in the form of pleading in the <hi>Courts.</hi> Thirdly in the Judgment or <hi>Sentence,</hi> to which may be annexed alſo the <hi>Execution</hi> upon the ſame.</p>
               <p>For the manner of ſummoning, or <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> citation (by that which was ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed in <hi>Rome)</hi> a man might of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <note place="margin">Difference in ſummoning or Citation.</note> without any proceſs, cite his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, and compel him by force to come into the Court; whence the <hi>phraſes</hi> of <hi>in Jus rapere, in Jus ducere</hi> and ſuch like, are uſed by <hi>Plautus, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race,</hi> and other authours. This was not in ure at any time within this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> but it hath been held better, and always fit, That there might be ſome proceſſe ſent forth, and ſo a plainer, more peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and lawful courſe ſhould be
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53249:26"/> taken, (as if the King who is the head and fountain of <hi>Juſtice</hi> or the Judge under him had been firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the <hi>Suite)</hi> the like courſe was afterwards and is now taken in the Civil Law. For a <hi>Citation</hi> by <hi>Math. Wiſenbich</hi> is defimed to be, <hi>actus Judicialis, ſeu Judicii praeparatorius quo is, quem coràm ſiſti opus eſt, Judicis mandato legitime vocatur, jur is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riendi cauſa;</hi> of which (according to other Civilians) he in his paratitles maketh three parts, 1. <hi>Praeceptio Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicis,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Three parts of a Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Civil Laws now uſed.</note> 2. <hi>Verbalis citatio nuncii,</hi> 3. <hi>ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem nuncii relatio, quae</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>niſi exactis appareat, non valet citatio.</hi> In theſe three parts of ſummoning or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, the Civil Laws and the Laws <note place="margin">The Writ of Summons in our Law goeth out in the Kings name in ſome Courts, but not ſo in the Civil Law.</note> of <hi>England</hi> do not diſagree, ſave that in <hi>England</hi> the Writ of Sommons in many Caſes, and in ſome Courts, goeth out in the Kings name. Alſo for the conventing and ſummoning of any man before the <hi>Judge,</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Liberty is given by the Law of <note place="margin">By the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Law one might not convent a Magiſtrate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>England,</hi> than was antiently allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Civil Law. For by the Civil Law, a man might not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a Magiſtrate, nor <hi>Judge,</hi> nor
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53249:26"/> one that was marrying a wife, or a man that is performing the Funerals of his friend, or a man that is pleading or following his Cauſe before a Judge, <hi>nee parentem patronum; parentes pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troni in Jus</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Praetor) ſine permiſſu meo, ne quis vocet.</hi> But by the <note place="margin">None exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted from Suite by the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </note> Laws of <hi>England,</hi> none are exempted from Suite; only <hi>Dukes, Earles, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> and their Wives are priviledged, that a man cannot attach or take their perſons by <hi>Capias,</hi> both for the honour of Nobility, and becauſe it is ſuppoſed they are never without ſome goods or land, which may ſatisfy the Debts. But if the action be againſt the Crown and Dignity, or <hi>Contra pacem,</hi> then for their violence, their bodies alſo were ſubject to the Kings Writ. The ſame Law is of <hi>Abbots,</hi> and <hi>Priors.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The Civil Law allowed more exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions from appearing to Suits than the Law of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note> But the Civil Law alloweth a greater Liberty, and ſaith generally, <hi>eas per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonas quibus reverentia praeſtanda eſt, ſine juſſu Praetoris in Jus vocare non licet.</hi> And yet although the Civil Law be more liberal in allowing exemptions from Citation, and ſummoning of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to appear, than is our Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> notwithſtanding there is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53249:27"/> betwixt theſe Laws in the form of Suite and pleading upon divers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs (wherein theſe two Laws might perhaps correct each other) whereof but a touch ſhall be given at this time, and it may be more ſhall be ſaid at the concluſion of this tract, when the remedy and redreſs of ſome things conceived to be amiſs in our Laws ſhall be ſpoken of.</p>
               <p>The ſecond point concerning the <note place="margin">The ſecond difference in the form of pleading.</note> difference betwixt our Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the Civil Laws being in the form of pleading and diverſities of proceſs; For the firſt, which is the form of pleading, only they agree in this, That both the Laws have had a ſpecial reſpect of nice obſervation, and alſo have endured alteration in pleading. For firſt the Civil Law, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that in <hi>Rome</hi> the <hi>Decemviri</hi> had gotten the Law of the 12 Tables, and that Interpretation grew frequent upon them, then ſaith <hi>Pomponius, Ex his legibus, eodem fere tempore, actiones compoſitae ſunt, quibus inter ſe homines diſceptarent, quas actiones ne populus ut vellet inſtitueret, certas ſolenneſque eſſe voluerunt, &amp; appellata haec pars juris,</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:53249:27"/> 
                  <hi>legis actiones; id eſt, legitimae actiones:</hi> and immediatly after ſaith he, <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um harum interpretandi ſcientia &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiones apud Collegium pontificum erant,</hi> &amp;c. Afterwards the Actions were, (as <hi>Livy</hi> reporteth) and the Book of them, gotten by <hi>C. Flavius</hi> Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to <hi>Appius Claudius,</hi> was by him publiſhed and ſo communicated to the common people, for which they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on him the Tribuneſhip and other <hi>Magiſtracies;</hi> they called that Book <hi>Jus Civile Flavianum:</hi> Like to which alſo <hi>Sextus Aelius</hi> framed ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which was called after his name <hi>Jus Aelianum.</hi> Theſe <hi>formulae Juris</hi> were uſed very ſtrictly; for ſaith <hi>We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenbechius, Olim ut omnia ordine, &amp; recte procederent, &amp; ne temere, ſineque cauſa quis ad jurgia &amp; lites conudaret: impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trandum erat à praetore judicium, qui actori poſtulatam à ſe actionem impertie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur, &amp; formulam agendi diſceptandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que pedaneo judici, &amp; litigatoribus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribebat.</hi> So that then by the Civil Law, the planitiffe did get his form of pleading from the <hi>Judge,</hi> or <hi>Praetor,</hi> which was afterwards upon expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of inconvenience altered by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53249:28"/> the reſcript of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> (which <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinian</hi> hath put in his <hi>Code)</hi> likewiſe <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Valentinian</hi> hath done the ſame. But the difference betwixt this and the pleading of our Common Law is, That at no time was the <note place="margin">A ſtrict form of pleading required but not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by our Laws.</note> plaintiffe tied by the Common Laws of <hi>England</hi> to receive his whole form of pleading from the <hi>Judge,</hi> although it be true that he is required to ſet down a ſtrict form of pleading ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law upon his own peril.</p>
               <p>Alſo another difference there is, in <note place="margin">Different forms of pleading in our own Law in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Courts and much more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt both the Laws.</note> the forms of pleading betwixt theſe two Laws. Firſt, that our forms of pleading do differ according to the different forms of pleadings and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations in ſeveral Courts, which the Civil Law doth not. Secondly, and particularly, the form of pleading in the Civil Law is, in all actions perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal (becauſe they do <hi>ex obligatione tanquam cauſa proxima competere actori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus)</hi> in the Libel you muſt expreſs the remote Cauſe and not only the next Cauſe: as for example, I lend mony to <hi>Titius,</hi> now I may have an Action againſt him for it; The remote cauſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53249:28"/> is the lending, the next and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate of the Action is the <hi>obligatio</hi> as they call it. Now if I Libel againſt <hi>Titius,</hi> if I ſay, <hi>Ago ad decem, ad quae Titius eſt mihi obligatus.</hi> This is naught, ſaith <hi>Minſinger</hi> (ſhewing it out of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">The Civil Law in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal actions doth expreſs the remote cauſe in the Libel, but in real actions the next Cauſe.</note> authorities) becauſe the remote Cauſe is not in the Libel: But if that had been in alone, that had been good, as <hi>Mutuam Titio decem, pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o eum condemnari.</hi> But in real Actions they go <hi>inverſa via,</hi> putting in always the next Cauſe, but not of necceſſity the remote; (but at the pleaſure of the Advocate) as, <hi>Peto fundum iſtum à Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pronio, quia ejuſdem ſum dominus fundi;</hi> here the <hi>dominium</hi> is the <hi>Cauſa proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma;</hi> and if the Advocate dare venture it, he may ſay alſo, <hi>ſum dominus quia emi;</hi> where the remote Cauſe is alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. A very nice difference which is not exacted in the form of pleadings <note place="margin">How in our Law the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and next Cauſe are both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in all actions.</note> in our Law. But it is uſual with us, that in every Mans real, perſonal, and mixt Actions, the <hi>Cauſa propinqua</hi> and <hi>remota</hi> are both put in the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yet ſo that in the Common Pleas in the Writ commonly is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the next Cauſe, and in the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53249:29"/> Declaration which containeth the Writ alſo, the remote Cauſe (but in ſome the Writ doth contain the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) as in waſt, the Writ <hi>quare fecit vaſtum in terris quas tenuit ex dimiſſione ad exhaereditationem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> here is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Cauſe: But in Action of Debt, <hi>praecipe quod reddat vj. libr. quas debet;</hi> here is the next Cauſe and the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration contains the remote, as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, Bargain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Neither is there any Declaration in our Laws (as the form is now uſed) but contains both Cauſes in it: beſides there are other differences betwixt the forms uſed in the pleadings and declarations of both the Laws, which would be too long and tedious to recite.</p>
               <p>The next difference is in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <note place="margin">3. The third difference in the award<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</note> awarded in both the Laws. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the awarding of Proceſs we find that with us in perſonal actions (I mean in many of them joyning Statute Law and Common Law to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) <note place="margin">In Actions perſonal more Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our Law than by the Civil Law.</note> there are commonly awarded (if the Suite be commenced in the Common Pleas) ſummons, attach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, diſtreſs, three <hi>capias</hi> with an <hi>exigent</hi> at the laſt, whereby the King
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53249:29"/> hath Title for the parties contumacy to his Goods and Chattels.</p>
               <p>So that the plaintiffe hath now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy by accident only, and if the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant appear and reverſe the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary, or get pardon and ſo anſwer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (which is a long time before this can be brought to paſs) and by this means this Suite may depend long, yet the defendant never convented, but at two or three years end, the plaintiffe may be driven to declare anew (as if he had but then begun his Suite.) But by the Civil Law, as the <hi>Pandects</hi> ſhew us, and <hi>Weſenbech</hi> affirmeth the Term to be now in the Empire, <hi>poſt abſentiam adverſarii, petat quis edictum primum, mox alterum, per intervallum (non minus decem dierum) &amp; tertium: quibus propoſitis, tunc peremptoriè impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tret, quod inde hoc nomen ſumpſit, quod perimeret diſceptationem, hoc eſt ultra non pateretur adverſarium tergiverſari.</hi> Then if the defendant appear at the day given him by the <hi>Peremptory edict,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">No judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the plaintiffe at the Civil Law.</note> or if he do not, the matter ſhall be diſcuſſed, and judgment given for him whoſe part ſhall be found beſt. But if the plaintiffe appear not, then
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:53249:30"/> nothing ſhall be done but <hi>circumdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendum erit edictum perpetuum.</hi> And the peremptory edict may at the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Judge be granted, at the firſt by the ſame authority: So that <note place="margin">The intereſt of the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe leſſe ſubject to prejudice in Actions per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonals by the Civil Law than by our Law.</note> hereby the Intereſt of the party who hath right, is leſs ſubject to prejudice by that Law than by ours. And this courſe of the Civil Law doth not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſo much delay as doth our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law. For by our Law in ſuch Caſes where no Outlawry lieth in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Actions, there the Proceſs of diſtreſs goeth out infinitely, and then is there no end of the Suite, as in <hi>per quae ſervicia, quae juris clamat,</hi> and ſuch like; wherein it is true, that our Law ſeverely puniſheth the party which ſo much ſheweth contumacy to the Law, yet doth it no good or very little to the plaintiffe for his ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>But there is another difference, that in Actions altogether real, as Entry, Eſcheate, Right, Dower, and ſuch like, the remedy allowed by the Laws of <hi>England</hi> is far better; for in them if at the day appointed, upon the firſt ſummons, the party make default, and the <hi>quarto diepoſt</hi> be paſt, then is
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53249:30"/> there a <hi>graund cape</hi> to take his land in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the King, and the plaintiffe ſhall have it from the King by judgment if the defendant do not come to replevy it by oath, that he was not ſummoned according to the Law or ſuch like (always remembred that <hi>Eſſoynes</hi> upon juſt occaſion may herein breed much delay.) And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is there much difference betwixt the Civil Law and our Law, for in the Civil Law upon their peremptory edict, notwithſtanding the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant <note place="margin">A main dif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the proceeding of our Law and the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Law in Actions real.</note> doth not appear, the right ſhall be examined and thereupon judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given, but with us upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault at the <hi>graund cape,</hi> the plaintiffe ſhall have the land by judgment al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the right be not examined. As alſo upon the appearance if by oath he cannot ſave the firſt default, likewiſe if he once appear and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards make default, before judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given there muſt be a <hi>petit cape</hi> awarded, at which Writs return if he do not ſave the firſt default, there ſhall be judgment given againſt him. That all this was antient Law may be ſeen in <hi>Bractons</hi> Treatiſe <hi>de defaltis.</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:53249:31"/> So that in perſonal actions the Civil <note place="margin">In perſonal actions the Civil Law is more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, but in real more remiſs than our Law of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note> Law hath a more ſevere and ſpeedy courſe for recovery than the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law of <hi>England,</hi> but in real a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions it is ſomewhat more remiſs, or at the leaſt ours is more ſevere.</p>
               <p>For the laſt difference ſpoken of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <note place="margin">4. The laſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is in the giving and Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> theſe Laws which is for the giving of judgment and Execution upon the ſame in real actions being in <hi>rem,</hi> although the form and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance thereof may be divers, yet in theſe real actions <hi>quoad ſubſtantiam &amp; effectum,</hi> the difference is not very great, for both Laws muſt make Execution of the ſame thing, though perchance not in the ſame manner; But for perſonal actions it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by the courſe of antient and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent times that for Debt ever ſince King <hi>Edward</hi> the third his time, and damages and accompt ever ſince <hi>Henry</hi> the third his time, in actions upon the Caſe ever ſince King <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th. his time, and in all actions <note place="margin">Execution againſt the perſon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by our Law in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal.</note> where <hi>Capias</hi> lieth in the Proceſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore judgment, there <hi>Capias ad ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaciendum</hi> lieth after judgment to put the party in priſon for Execution;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:53249:31"/> than the which although a more ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous Law were by the 12 Tables, whereby <hi>Corpus inter creditores ſecari licebat</hi> (whereof <hi>Rivallius</hi> ſaith an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample is not read in any Hiſtory or other Book) yet afterwards by their <hi>Lex Petilia</hi> it was decreed (as <hi>Livy</hi> reporteth) that no man ſhould be for Debt, <hi>nervo aut compedibus vinctus,</hi> which notwithſtanding was uſed ſometimes by the violence of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> and therefore ſometimes renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Laws <hi>Portia, Sempronia, Popilia,</hi> and other, whereby <hi>terga ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vium</hi> were made <hi>tanquam ſacroſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta.</hi> Alſo by the <hi>Lex Julia,</hi> if the Debtor would leave his goods his Body was free, as appears by the ſame, reported in the <hi>Code;</hi> But this Law <hi>Hottoman</hi> thinketh not to extend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Banquerupts,</hi> or ſuch as are <hi>non ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendo</hi> by their own default. But by the <hi>Anthentiques</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Law, if <note place="margin">The Civil Law more mild of lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter time than ours for Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt ones perſon in debt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> a man were poor by ſome external misfortune and not by his own means, if he would <hi>ejurare copiam bonam,</hi> he need not leave his goods for his Creditors, nor ſubject himſelf to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; which is ſo mild a Law towards
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:53249:32"/> Debtors, that it hath no proportion with ours. But where by our Law we do not admit that Beaſt for the Plough ſhall be taken upon <hi>Elegit fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias</hi> which is conſtituted by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the ſecond (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that be referred by <hi>Polydore</hi> to <hi>Mulmuſius</hi> Law) therein the Law of this Kingdom agreeth with the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Law, as it appeareth in the <hi>Code:</hi> ſo that we ſhew in the Execution of judgments there are ſome differences even in the Civil Law it ſelf accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the alteration of times; at the firſt far more ſevere, but in the end much more mild. And alſo by theſe forementioned examples there are differences betwixt the Civil Law, and our Laws of <hi>England</hi> in the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution <note place="margin">The Civil Law diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from it ſelf in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent times for Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on mens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> of their judgments. Many more differences might be found, both in this and in the other forenamed points betwixt both the Laws, if time did ſerve or were required to ſearch and ſet down the ſame. But this may ſuffice as a taſt for this time and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:53249:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>An anſwer to certain Objections uſually made againſt the Laws of</hi> England.</head>
               <p>BY way of imputation or indeed of Scandal, there are uſually amongſt others, theſe Objections made againſt our Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That they are written in a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſpeech; even to Scholars un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known or not underſtood.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That they are framed without <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Method or order.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That they have no Maximes, or <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> fundamental grounds whereon they conſiſt, or at the leaſt not ſuch as are certain.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That the Judges opinion (which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> may be extended according to <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane affection)</hi> doth make or alter the Law: ſo that it conſiſteth not (ſay they) in <hi>ſcrinio principis,</hi> that is, in the Records of the State, but in <hi>ſcrinio pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoris</hi> of the Judge; the key whereof the Judge may alter, and by a new lock faſtened on, make a way to come
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53249:33"/> at unheard of reaſon, according to his own conceipts, which muſt be admitted for Law, at the leaſt for the time.</p>
               <p>For the firſt Objection, I conceive <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> it to flow rather from ſome ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain miſlike before the matter be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, or elſe ſome quaint and dainty palate, who diſtaſts all things (be the matter never ſo ſound and ſubſtantial) which doth not ſavour of perfumed eloquence, and poliſhed phraſes of Rhetorick, than upon due conſideration of the language it ſelf; for although it muſt be confeſſed, that the ſpeech and phraſe wherein our Law is written is rude and unpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, in reſpect that no Nation ſpeaks it as it is now written, and that the ſame Nation from whence it is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved cannot underſtand it preciſely without inſtruction, yet that it is ſimply Barbarous, or that thereby the Law receiveth any diſgrace may well be denied. For firſt, admitting there were no other aide in the defence hereof, than that which the Lord chief <hi>Juſtice Cooke</hi> hath in his preface to his third Book of Reports, <hi>Siquidem</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:53249:33"/> 
                  <hi>relationum iſtarum phraſis aut ſtylus ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi minus arrideat, ut rei ipſius ſubjectae praeſtantia atque utilitas, &amp; delectet &amp; ſatisfaciat? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde fiat ut totum te ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirabili plane dulcedini cogitationis at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſcientiae dedas &amp; addices.</hi> Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that this were the effect of the defence, ſurely we alone ſhould not be driven to this ſhift, to praiſe only the matter, and to reject or omit complements of form; for let the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents herein but view other facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (which they that profeſs thoſe faculties would have to excel either of the Laws <hi>multis paraſangis)</hi> obſerve <note place="margin">Other Arts written in as ill ſtile and phraſe, as is our Law.</note> but the excellent part of the mixt <hi>Mathematiques,</hi> as judicial <hi>Aſtrologie,</hi> it will not be denied but ſome, nay moſt of their antienteſt Authors (eſpecially which wrote in <hi>Latine)</hi> do by their Barbariſm in the <hi>Roman</hi> tongue, equal the worſt ſeeming <hi>Soloeciſmes</hi> in our Common Laws: witneſs hereof <hi>Haly Ben Rodan</hi> his Comment upon the <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dripartite</hi> of <hi>Ptolomy</hi> in <hi>Latine,</hi> to whom may be added <hi>Guido Bonatus</hi> moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, with <hi>Alchabitius</hi> and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes de Saxonia</hi> his paraphraſe upon him; it may be truly ſaid, that a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53249:34"/> in <hi>Weſtminſter-hall</hi> for <hi>Latine,</hi> or a Caſe argued in a private Inn of Court moote for <hi>French,</hi> ſhall reſpectively in many phraſes and good words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed moſt of theſe authours, nay in this Art the beſt tongued authour (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Julius Firmious)</hi> is accounted the <note place="margin">The beſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in ſome Arts writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the worſt phraſe and ſtile.</note> worſt <hi>Artiſt.</hi> How many <hi>Latine</hi> phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or words are there to be found in the ſide of a leaf in any of the chiefeſt and antienteſt School Divines (who reſpected not the language, but the points of learning which they hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.) Neither in this, or almoſt in any other ſtudy doth the language add to the Art, ſeeing that as the ancient <hi>Hieroglyphical</hi> notes to expreſs words and ſyllables were added only as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of memory and tradition, and in other Arts the <hi>voces ſecundae intentionis</hi> (as the <hi>Logicians</hi> call them) <note place="margin">Terms of Art do not give grace, but help to learn the Art.</note> being the Terms of Art, give no grace to the ſtudy or language, but only help to learn the Art whereof they are written; therefore the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is but an inſtrument to the ſcience which it contains, and is as it were the Table wherein is pictured the ſence of the Law. So the <hi>Civilians</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:53249:34"/> ſay, <hi>tabula picturae cedit,</hi> and yet moſt modern languages (nay in a manner all) have bene forced to borrow from <note place="margin">Moſt lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row words of others.</note> other, words, and names, eſpecially of Art and invention: neither can the lofty ſtiled <hi>Greek,</hi> or the more penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious yet pleaſant <hi>Latine,</hi> name all things in their own language accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their proper Nature, except they participate of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> which doth name things according to their Nature, but that cannot be done by any other language ſo fully.</p>
               <p>Beſides all this, it may be ſhewed that the ſpeech wherein the Law is written, is not to be ſo much diſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>in ſuo genere;</hi> for it appeareth by the Hiſtories of ancient time, that when the <hi>Normans</hi> came hither, the <note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the pleading and Statutes to be done in French.</note> pleading of Law, Statutes, and ſuch like things were commanded to be all in <hi>French;</hi> ſo ſaith the <hi>Abbot</hi> of <hi>Croy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Normani enim ipſum idioma tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum abhorrebant, quod leges terrae, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutaque Anglicorum Regum lingua Gallica tractarentur, &amp; pueris etiam in ſcholis principia literarum grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum Gallicè &amp; non Anglicè traderen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Whereupon (as it appears) our
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:53249:35"/> Statutes which are extant, eſpecially thoſe of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt his time (though not all) <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and ſo forward, were the reports in the Nature of <hi>reſponſa prudentum</hi> among the <hi>Romans,</hi> taken and publiſhed in <hi>French,</hi> which then was not accounted Barbarous, for in likelyhood it was the ſame language which at the firſt was ſpoken amongſt the <hi>Normans;</hi> and ſo were all Pleas at the Barr pleaded in <hi>French</hi> until the 36. of <hi>Edward</hi> the 3. which although it were not ſo good <hi>French</hi> as <hi>Duber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> his days and weeks, yet it came then in a manner near to <hi>Froſſard</hi> his <note place="margin">Our Laws written at the firſt in French came then near the ſpeech at that time uſed.</note> 
                  <hi>French</hi> in his Hiſtory (which was made about that time) as <hi>Apuleius</hi> his <hi>Latine</hi> being no <hi>Roman,</hi> did unto the phraſes of <hi>Livy, Cicero,</hi> and ſuch like. Some corruption there muſt needs be in tract of time, of a tongue ſpoken in another Country, and conſonant with another different language, as the <hi>French</hi> was here. It is evident that the antient Books, as <hi>Britton, Heng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and the year Books of the firſt ſucceeding ages are in better <hi>French</hi> than our later Books are, becauſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:53249:35"/> our common Lawyers now do imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the antients in ſuch words, as they have there learned, and if they want a fit word in <hi>French,</hi> then do they as Sr. <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> ſaith of <hi>Lalus,</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Gallicis ſi quid nequit vocabulis,</l>
                  <l>Conat id verbis licet non Gallicis,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Canore ſaltem perſonare Gallico,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
               <p>So that indeed, the tongue wherein <note place="margin">Our Law French of later times much min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled.</note> the Law is publiſhed of late hath been much mingled with <hi>French, Latine,</hi> and ſome <hi>Engliſh;</hi> that a man might compare it to that ſuppoſition of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race, Humano capiti, cervicem pictor equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> &amp;c. And our late Law <hi>French</hi> doth corrupt the antient Law <hi>French,</hi> as that in thoſe primitive times was corrupted ſome what by the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> ſo that the moſt of our Law being in the ancient <hi>French</hi> (for ſo are the year Books until <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th his time incluſively) deſerveth no more to be ill thought on for the language (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not ſpoken in our or in any Country) than <hi>Plautus</hi> his Comedies becauſe they agree not with <hi>Latine</hi> Authors in their <hi>Latine,</hi> or <hi>Chaucers</hi> writings becauſe in words &amp; ſtile they
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:53249:36"/> differ ſo much from Sr. <hi>Philip Sidneys</hi> ſelected and exquiſite phraſe. Should any man think the worſe of the ſtudy of antiquity becauſe that moſt things wherewith they have dealt withal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">The ſtudy of antiquity not to be miſliked for the ill <hi>Latine.</hi>
                  </note> Hiſtories of the middle and later age on this ſide <hi>Chriſts</hi> nativity, are written for the moſt part in very mean <hi>Latine.</hi> Neither is it any good objection to ſay that our tongue, wherein the Law is written, is no tongue, becauſe it is not ſpoken; for about <hi>Charlemain</hi> his time (as appears in <hi>Lipſius</hi> his epiſtles) the right <hi>French</hi> did more differ from, and ſeem more Barbarous in reſpect of the ſmoth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tongued now uſed in <hi>France,</hi> than our Law <hi>French</hi> about <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt <note place="margin">The ancient French more rude, than that now uſed.</note> his time did differ from the Natural <hi>French</hi> then in uſe; ſo as it was a tongue then much ſpoken, but now much varied and altered. Where it is objected that it is a tongue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known certainly: It is by ſtudents of the Law, as eaſily, and far more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learned than any other language can be; for within leſs than a ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nights ſtudy it will be indifferently underſtood. And that it ſhould not
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:53249:36"/> be commonly underſtood of all men, <note place="margin">Our Law <hi>French</hi> eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. Fit that the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage wherein our Law is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſhould not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood.</note> there is great reaſon and no profit but peril in the contrary; (for if all men (whereof the greateſt number are of unquiet ſpirits) ſhould at the firſt fight underſtand the language wherein our Laws are written, that would breed but ſmall reſt to them that would moſt deſire peace.) There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I cannot ſee what impeachment of credit it is to our Laws that they are written in ſuch a language, if of themſelves they are not to be diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, which in the other points will ſomewhat appear.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond objection that our <note place="margin">2. The ſecond objection, that our Laws do want Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</note> Laws want Method and order: For Method which indeed in all learning is to be wiſhed for, (and yet is not found or framed in our Laws) but that is no great diſgrace to the Laws, for hardly ſhall we find any faculty that is without any defect (as Sr. <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> in his ſecond Book of the advancement of learning hath well noted) whereas alſo there is not an harder point in Logick and Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, than the right diſtinguiſhing of the true Methodical parts in any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53249:37"/> as appears by the multitude of writers in each faculty. Indeed the <note place="margin">Long, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Law was brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Method.</note> Civil Law was eaſier for Students af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch time as <hi>Juſtinian</hi> had digeſted the 2000 Books and 300000 verſes, wherein it was ſcatered and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? the like whereof might be wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our Laws; but upon what grounds hoped for, I cannot yet <note place="margin">The difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting our Laws into a Method.</note> diſcerne; for no ſmall impediment therein would be, ſeeing our Laws are grounded ſo much upon reaſon, which alters and reforms other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent errors. Hardly could there be a Methodical digeſt drawn of all the year Books (I mean for authority and not only for Study) which might be ſure to ſtand always firm for Law, without it were firſt ſo determined by <hi>Parliament,</hi> the confirmation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I conceive would come <hi>ad Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das Graecas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But for Study the time may come <note place="margin">A private Method for ſtudy, more eaſy and profitable.</note> that by the example of <hi>Littleton</hi> for <hi>Tenures,</hi> and Common Law convei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, and Eſtates; <hi>Stanford</hi> for the Crown pleas; <hi>Theloal</hi> for Writs; <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> for Warranty, and few more heads; <hi>Kitchin</hi> for Courts; together
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:53249:37"/> with <hi>Crompton,</hi> and <hi>Lambard;</hi> ſo by their example, ſome great Lawyers may ſettle themſelves to imitation; this perchance may be remedied by ſome skilful <hi>Scholaſtical</hi> Lawyer, but whether the remedy would not be worſe than the diſeaſe, and whether it will not make any truants of ſuch as otherwiſe might prove painful Students, let it be their judgments who are judicial, and not theirs who are altogether ignorant in our Laws; <note place="margin">What in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting of our Law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a preciſe Method.</note> for this is moſt to be feared; which we find by experience, that where abridgments are, and where by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Method ſome ſtrive to give life and luſter unto the Art they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs; the Students thereof coveting to come the next way to their Jornies end, do like thoſe Travellers which to avoid ſome long (though the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer) way, do chooſe to adventure the paſſage over a bridge, whoſe foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may yet be faulty, &amp; ſo fall ſhort of their Journey, rather than to go ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what farther unto a ford where there is leſs danger and a ſurer, though ſomewhat a longer paſſage. I will not ſay that there is the like hazard in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:53249:38"/> Methodical compoſition of our anuals, or year Books of the Law, but ſure we ſee that many Students are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy more addicted to the Study of the new than of the old year Books, <note place="margin">The peril, that Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents deſire to read the new and to omit the old Books of our Law.</note> wherein ſeeking to ſave pains ſome may fortune to find in the end, that to offer to go a nearer way than is to be found, is (as the proverb is) but the next way about; for though it be true that the laſt Judged Caſes are moſt in force, and the former many times abrogated, or altered, yet the old Caſes give grounds of Law unto the new, and by peruſing both, the differences of Reaſons which make the one firm and the other to fail are beſt diſcerned.</p>
               <p>So that ſurely there is no humane <note place="margin">No Study requires more the reading of old and new Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, than doth our Law.</note> ſcience which requireth more the revolution of old and new, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Precedent and Subſequent matters, and in concluſion, that exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth more the Study of the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of that ſcience, than doth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Study of the whole volumes of our Law, to make a man to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Lawyer: therefore whether this Compendious digeſting our Law into
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:53249:38"/> Method, be profitable, neceſſary, or hurtful to the Students thereof; though, I muſt confeſs, I do much affect Method (as holding it a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal light of Learning) yet, as I ſaid before, I muſt leave the Cenſure thereof unto the Oracles of the Law. But if any man will be deſirous to follow a method in the Study of the Law, or a method for his Memory when he hath ſtudied it; he might, by diſtinguiſhing aright ſuch Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betical <note place="margin">Diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabetical Titles, a help only for Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</note> Titles as are diſperſed in <hi>Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herbert, Brook</hi> and <hi>Statham,</hi> their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgments, find, for his private ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and uſe, a far more orderly and profitable form, than the reading of theſe Books according to <hi>A B C,</hi> do admit. Yet this, as the reſt, is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken under correction of better Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Under this head of want of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, <note place="margin">Another ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this head againſt our Laws.</note> is comprehended another ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection which ſome make, and find fault withall; That our Pleaders uſe no Method, Eloquence, or Art in their Pleadings. If they mean the Pleadings which are entred in the Rolls, had they once tried ſome tickle
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:53249:39"/> points of exception (as perchance others have done to their charge and peril) they would be of another opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and it may be then they would complain of the contrary; that in the rules and directions for <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pleadings in Rolls and at the Bar, not <hi>Ciceronian,</hi> but diſtinct and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant enough.</note> 
                  <hi>Traverſes, Confeſſions</hi> and <hi>Avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances,</hi> there are too nice differences and diſtinctions ſometimes exacted. If they intend the Pleading and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments at the Barr; it is true, that for Form they uſe neither <hi>Ciceronian</hi> Orations, nor <hi>Syllogiſtical</hi> Arguments in Mood and Figure; but yet, for matter, they do ſmell (as <hi>Phocion</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> Orations) of the Candle, moſt commonly, in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring of great pains taken, with exact quotation of Books and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Neither ſhould there be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected <note place="margin">Eloquent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives or inſinuations not fit for the pleaders of Law.</note> in ſuch Arguments elegant Forms of Speech, ſuch as ſhould tend to the commending or diſpraiſing of the parties (as the old Orators, <hi>Iſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> and his ſucceſſors were wont;) And if any uſe this, as ſome do, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of this Eloquence is too much. For Syllogiſms, indeed they uſe them not, neither are they needful in this
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:53249:39"/> Art, or kind of Arguing, but as they are fitteſt for the Schools and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, ſo if there were need of them, there is no doubt but moſt of their Arguments or Pleadings at the Bar, might by Scholars be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into Syllogiſms, though then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance <note place="margin">Syllogiſms fitteſt for the Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Schools.</note> the concurring reaſons of the Law might be made more intricate, and as hard to be underſtood as <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotles Acromantica,</hi> eſpecially of ſuch as are not Logicians.</p>
               <p>Now to the laſt objection againſt <note place="margin">The laſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Laws.</note> our Laws, that they have not funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Maxims which are univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true, and that the Judges private opinions do uſually alter the Laws, and ſo leave it alwayes in uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: For the firſt, concerning Maxims, or certain Foundations, which they ſuppoſe are not in our Laws; They which read and underſtand the Law ſhall find, that there are many recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <note place="margin">Many rules received in our Law without any contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> opinions and Rules in the Law, whereof ſcarce any contradiction hath been of Opinion, much leſs of Judgment; as amongſt the reſt, theſe of Inheritances.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:53249:40"/>
               <p>That no land can by Inheritance <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> lineally aſcend.</p>
               <p>That the Heirs of the part of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Father are to be preferred before the Heirs of the part of the Mother.</p>
               <p>That of Inheritances deſcended by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the Mother, the Heirs of the part of the Father cannot inherit, and ſo of the other ſide.</p>
               <p>With many other ſuch Rules in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible and unchangeable in the Law, whereof divers are collected by <hi>Sainct German</hi> in his firſt book.</p>
               <p>And the grounds or maxims are ſo certain concerning ſome of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt parts of the Law; <hi>(viz.</hi> about the Inheritances and Eſcheats) that the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Coke</hi> affirmeth (who is beſt able to prove his aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) he found not in all the time he ſtudied the Law: <hi>Ne duas quidem adverti quaeſtiones, de jure heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, de terrarum ligitima confiſcatione, ſive (ut loquantur) eſcaeta, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſque conſimilibus.</hi> But howſoever this opinion ſtands, It is moſt ſure, that there are infinite other Rules and Poſitions in the Law, which admit no alteration or queſtion. To
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53249:40"/> which it is uſually replied; It is true, that there are many ſuch Rules and Poſitions in the Common Law, which remain ſtill firm, and are not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted, yet they are not Maxims, nor <note place="margin">That the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive rules of our law may be in ſome ſort reckoned as Maxims.</note> deſerve not that title, as other Arts have, and are allowed them. The anſwer is, that theſe poſitive Rules which are certainly ſet down and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined for infallible, may, without any great errour, be intitled Maxims of the Law, or at leaſt, held in the nature of them (for authority, if not for method.) For in any Art, (as to inſtance in <hi>Geometry)</hi> let a propoſition or <hi>theoreme</hi> be once infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly demonſtrated by principles; the Mathematician who made this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, upon infallible tokens of truth, may not unfitly call his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration a <hi>Maxime,</hi> or Principle, in reſpect of authority, though not of method, as was ſpoken before: the like may be ſaid of our infallible poſitions and demonſtrations in the Common Law, whereof there are very many, howſoever ſome conceive the contrary.</p>
               <p>To ſhape ſome anſwer unto the laſt
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:53249:41"/> moſt uſual &amp; effectual objection made againſt our Laws; that is, that the Judges private opinions and reaſon do uſually alter the Laws: and ſo it is left alwaies in a Labyrinth of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty. Although my judgment in the Laws being ſo ſlender, is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to anſwer ſo important an objection, tending ſo much to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of our Laws, and indeed to the great ſcandal of the Juſtice of this Realm (the execution whereof de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth moſt on theſe Judgments ſuppoſed to be ſo uncertain) yet I will be bold to ſpeak what I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, leaving the more full anſwer hereof to them that are much more deeply learned in our Laws.</p>
               <p>Where they ſay that the alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">How the Judges opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions may alter the Law.</note> of the Laws doth depend on the Judges particular opinions and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whereby it is ſo much ſubject to mutability; ſure this is not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther true, in ſuch ſence as it is ſpoken; for it is not the private opinion of one Judge that altereth the Law, but it is the concurring opinion of more than one, and that not only concurring in their private reaſon
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:53249:41"/> and ſence as it is ſaid, but their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are alwayes conferred with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Judgments, and either thereby ſtrengthened, or if differing from the ſame, they muſt ſhew reaſon alſo ſtronger or different from the former to ground their Judgments upon. And in this ſort that latter Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhould reverſe former, is not unuſual in other Laws, nor peculiar only to this of ours, for ſaith the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Law, <hi>Non eſt novum ut priores leges</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">That the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Law doth allow the alteration of Laws and of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> 
                  <hi>ad poſteriores trahantur.</hi> The Civil Law hath the like rule in another place, and the ſame hath a great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, and a Learned Politician, <hi>Non poſſunt omnes articuli ſingulatim aut legibus, aut Senatus conſultis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendi, ſed cum in aliqua cauſa ſententia eorum manifeſta eſt, is qui juriſdictioni praeeſt, ad ſimilia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedere atque ita jus dicere debet.</hi> In like manner concludeth a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <note place="margin">The opinion of a learned Father of the Church concerning the alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Laws.</note> and an ancient Eccleſiaſtical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, concerning the alteration of Laws upon good grounds of reaſon; He ſaith, <hi>Ideo quia antiquiores leges ad poſteriores trahi uſitatum eſt; ſemper quaſi hoc legibus ineſſe credi oportet; ut</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:53249:42"/> 
                  <hi>ad eas quoque perſonas pertineant quae quandoque ſimiles ſunt.</hi> But ſome will ſay, theſe are indeed rules for the alteration of Laws, upon different opinions and grounds of Reaſon; but have you any precedent that the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in other Laws do differ ſo much in their opinions, and do leave their Laws ſo uncertain? Yes ſurely, for in the Civil Law there are many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of great conſequence, wherein the Doctors do differ in opinion, and <note place="margin">In the Civil Law the Doctors do much differ in Opinion.</note> ſhew each of them ſeveral reaſons and authorities to uphold their ſides and opinions, for they differ much upon the expoſition of the Rules of their Law, which are drawn, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and reſtrain'd according to their ſeveral Opinions and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; the reaſon is rendred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a very hard matter to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs all particulars by comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion under a general head. But where it is ſaid, that the Law dependeth upon the variable reaſons of the Judges, that Reaſon ſhould be the ground both of the Law it ſelf, and of their Judgments upon the Law, is neither ſtrange nor unfit: for we
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:53249:42"/> confeſs that the Law is grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on tryed and well-examined Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which conſidereth what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, and what is inconvenient; what is for the general good, and what for the particular; what doth concurr with the rigour of Juſtice, and what with the moderation of Equity; with many other conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble circumſtances, which Reaſon doth deliver, as well to the Law-maker, as to the Judge in expounding the Law. But yet the Judges do not wholly and only rely on the rules of Reaſon in delivering the Law (as the ſole prop and pillar thereof) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though our Laws, as even the Laws of Nations, and all other particular and municipal Laws, are deduced from it: for <hi>ratio eſt regula aequitatis.</hi> And although the praiſe of the Law is, that the rules thereof are appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with reaſon (as the Touch-ſtone to try whether the remedy of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience be good and ſound;) yet Reaſon in our Law is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with other conſorts, and our Judges have other aids to ſupport and ſtrengthen their Judgments: being
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:53249:43"/> thoſe helps (which, as the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher ſaith) Reaſon doth uſe as her hand-maids, for the Invention and Knowledge of other Sciences and Arts, as Senſe, Obſervation, Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and Induction: Of Senſe, to ſingle out Notions; of Obſervation, to keep many Notions together; of Experience, to confer theſe Notions which are neceſſary, and which not; and by Induction of many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars concurring, to frame under few heads many general Concluſions. As other Sciences, and the perfect Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of them have theſe helps, ſo have our Law makers the ſame in Ordaining, and our Judges in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding of the Laws. The firſt, which is Senſe, is common to all men, (even in all Mechanical Arts;) but the latter (as Obſervation, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and Induction) are chief in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments uſed and applyed by our Judges in the interpretation and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding of our Laws: for after long ſtudy and practice of our Laws, after <note place="margin">What grounds the Judges do lay the Judgments upon.</note> the reading and revolving of former Judgments, and of other ſtudious la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; they come to Experience and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:53249:43"/> Obſervation, out of which they frame concluſions for future Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which muſt be ſtill like Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in like Caſes; for they may not, nor do not, ſo ſwerve from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Judgments, that they may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary them, without there appear ſome manifeſt difference of Reaſon, which their reading concurring with Obſervation, and Experience, can beſt inform them of; and then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on different reaſons, (wherein the latter may correct ſome ſlips of the former) to give different Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is neither ſtrange in our Law, unuſual in other Laws, or inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in either. Therefore they which frame theſe objections of contrariety and uncertainty in the Judgments of our Common Law (perchance for the moſt part) do not conceive the Reaſon of thoſe things which they condemn ſo much: and in this they are not much to be believed, nor over much to be blamed, if Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and not Malice, be the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; when they ſpeak as they think, not as they know.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:53249:44"/>
               <p>And for that many think (who <note place="margin">The accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Laws, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not all written, nor certainly ſet down.</note> think not much amiſs) that the chiefeſt defect of our Law is, becauſe it is not all written, or that it is not ſo written, that it is certain or ſure not to be changed. For the firſt, there is no other anſwer, as far as I can ſee, to be given, but that which was ſaid by a Writer of our Laws about three hundred years ſince: <hi>Si ob ſcripturae ſolummodo defectum, leges minime cenſentur; majoris proculdubio robur authoritatis, ipſis legibus videntur accommodare ſcripturae, quàm vel ratio ſtatuentis vel decernentis aequitas. Leges vero &amp; jura regni, ſcripto univerſaliter concludi noſtris temporibus, omnino qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem impoſſibile eſt, cùm propter ſcriben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium ignorantiam, tum propter earum multitudinem confuſam.</hi> It is confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therefore, that they are not all <note place="margin">Impoſſible that all the Law ſhould be written.</note> written, and acknowledged, that it is impoſſible they ſhould be all writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. And herein have we, for that part of the Common Law (which is generally called by that name) imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated the ancient <hi>Druides</hi> of this Land (but yet gone farther than they) who, following the <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:53249:44"/> did not commit their Learning to Writing, or rather the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> who, by the inſtitution of <hi>Licur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> held all Law not written, who, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> reporteth, <hi>exiguos illos &amp; pecuniarios contractus, quique prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter uſum vitae ſubinde immutantur, praeſtare cenſebat ſcriptis legibus non comprehendi, neque immobilibus conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinibus illigari: ſed permittendum ut pro ratione temporis augerentur, diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erentúrve, ſecundum probe inſtitutorum hominum arbitrium,</hi> yet our Law doth not give ſo much libertie to the <hi>Judges.</hi> But yet not onely <hi>Politicians</hi> and <hi>Moraliſts,</hi> but alſo the <hi>Civil law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers</hi> do permit that in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth the conſtitutions of <hi>Princes</hi> are to be interpreted according to the Judgment of Magiſtrates and Judges, ſometimes mitigated, and, according to incident diverſities, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted, which cannot be alwaies committed to writing: for it cannot be alwaies the ſame, and this were rather to be wiſhed than to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for in our Laws: and I would that he which finds this fault, could finde a remedie and preſcribe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:53249:45"/> Controverſies and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguities are ſo frequent not onely in this, but in all ſciences, arts and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, that every day new particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars <note place="margin">New parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars breed new queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> are ſubjects of new queſtions, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in the Laws, which ſpring out of the intricate forms of new Conveyances, and ſuch like inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men. And ſo long as man ſeeth but in <hi>aenigmate</hi> and <hi>per ſpeculum</hi> (as the <hi>Divines</hi> ſay of the Knowledg <note place="margin">How uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain man's knowledg is in Divine things and in other ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</note> of God) and ſo long as by the rules of the perſpectives, that which is ſeen by reflection, or refraction, is never ſeen in, or according to, his true place; ſo long and in ſuch ſort we muſt look for controverſies and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguities in all profeſſions, which are indeed not ſo much, or ſo ſenſibly felt, in any art as in the Law; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none other goeth ſo near mens <note place="margin">Nothing go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſo near to mens thoughts as their loſs of eſtate.</note> inward thoughts and conceipts as ſuch doe whereon their eſtates and poſſeſſions are adventured, therefore loſers may have leave to ſpeak, but not untruth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:53249:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the Books written of the Laws of</hi> England, <hi>whereby the Knowledge thereof is chiefly obtained.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE chief Knowledg (by ſtudy) <note place="margin">Three ſorts of writers of our Law.</note> of our Law doth conſiſt in the Works of them which have written of the Law, and they are of 3 ſorts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt whereof ſetteth down the Art and Rules of the ſame in a certain method, ſuch as is, <hi>Glanvill, Bracton</hi> and <hi>Britton,</hi> who are ancient Authors, wrote in <hi>Latine</hi> and did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to reduce thoſe Rules accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the titles of the <hi>Civil-lawes,</hi> but moſt eſpecially <hi>Bracton:</hi> though theſe are ancient Authors, yet they are now cited rather for ornament than for authoritie.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Others have written of the <note place="margin">Writers of the Nature and Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of Writs.</note> Precedents, Rules and Natures of Writs, which do lay the ground of every Action to procure judgment and execution thereon, as the books of <hi>Entries</hi> with the Regiſter, and the two <hi>books</hi> grounded thereupon.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:53249:46"/> In this <hi>Fitz-herbert</hi> hath deſerved ſpecially well.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A third ſort of Writers of our <note place="margin">Reporters of former Judged Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> Law there are, which be thoſe who write the particular and ſummary Caſes that have received Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Sentence in the King's ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cicial Courts, ſhewing how the Rules of Law were applied to thoſe Caſes, or rather how theſe Caſes were reduced to the Rules of Law both by the <hi>Counſellors</hi> that argued the ſame on both ſides, with proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reaſons confirming their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with authorities of former Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and alſo the <hi>Judges</hi> conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Sentences upon the ſame by the common ſquare of Reaſon and Rules they have learned of the foregoing learned <hi>Judges.</hi> Of this <note place="margin">It is not known who compiled the firſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nales and ancient Year-books.</note> latter ſort of Writers called Report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who they were that compiled the firſt and moſt antient Books of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports is not certain, for we have not their Names, but ſince the time of King <hi>Edward the third,</hi> there are ſome Works and Reports written of every King's Raign: for before his time we have not any <hi>Volume</hi> at
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:53249:46"/> large now left, and if any ſuch were, they are conſumed through the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury <note place="margin">Divers anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Year-books want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> of times, or neglect, or malice, of ſuch in whoſe cuſtody they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained: yet it ſhould ſeem, that in the raign of <hi>King Henry</hi> the 8. there were ſome more ancient Books or Reports of the Law Caſes extant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in the times of <hi>King Henry</hi> the 3. and <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, and <hi>Edw.</hi> the ſecond; for that <hi>Fitz-herbert</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Some Caſes abridged of the Books now not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant.</note> who did reduce all the Caſes of the Reports that were extant in his time under certain general Heads, and <hi>Brook</hi> likewiſe, who a little after him, did ſet forth another Abridgement of the Law, and Caſes extant in his time, (adding more general Heads than <hi>Fitz-herbert</hi> had done) yet both of them under divers of their titles abridge the pith of ſundry Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes argued, and moſt of them ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged in thoſe Kings raigns. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the Volumes at large are not <note n="†" place="margin">We have now E. 2. and R. 2. What Year-books are yet extant.</note> now extant.</p>
               <p>But of the Caſes which were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged in the time of King <hi>Edw.</hi> the third, there are four Volumes now extant. <hi>Of King</hi> Richard <hi>the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:53249:47"/> his time, there are not any Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes, but many Caſes abridged as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</hi> Of the times <hi>of King</hi> Henry <note place="margin">Long quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> 
                  <hi>the fourth and King</hi> Henry <hi>the fifth there is no Volume.</hi> Of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt there are two great Volumes. Of King <hi>Edw.</hi> the fourth one Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume. One Volume of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, in the later end of whoſe raign the Reports do diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue until the twelfth year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight. And then they were recontinued untill the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, from thence again diſcontinued till the twenty ſixt of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight; at which time they were held on for two years, that is, twenty ſixt and twenty ſeventh of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight: which are the laſt Reports which we have, ſave ſuch as ſince have been revived by three or four worthy men, whoſe private and voluntary diligence have for the publick good continued ſundry Reports, ſuch as Mr. <hi>Kellaway</hi> who reported pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately certain Caſes in King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh his time. This Book and labour is now come to light
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:53249:47"/> by Mr. Juſtice <hi>Crooke</hi> his Care and Charge. Alſo Mr. <hi>Brooke</hi> who did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port diverſe memorable Caſes which happened when he was making of his Abridgment in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, and Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> reported them under apt titles in his Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Then, my Lord <hi>Dyer,</hi> who, when <note place="margin">Of the late Reports of judged Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> he was a Student, a Practicioner and a Judge, obſerved many famous Caſes which were publiſhed ſince his death.</p>
               <p>A little after him began Mr. <hi>Plo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> who reported the ſpeciall Caſes which hapned from the ſecond of King <hi>Edw.</hi> the ſixt until the fifteenth of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> they are but few Caſes, yet more fully reported than any before him.</p>
               <p>Then, the voluntary Reporter is the late Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> who hath ſet forth thirteen Volumes of Reports. [Since that we have had <hi>Hobart, Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrod, Hutton,</hi> and divers others, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Juſtice <hi>Croke,</hi> who continues his Reports till the middle of the reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt.]</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:53249:48"/>
               <p>There are beſides theſe Reporters <note place="margin">Writers of Rules, and the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them to Caſes.</note> ſome other Writers of the Common Law, whoſe Works are mixt partly of Rules and partly of Application of them to certain Caſes of their own knowledg and collection: ſuch is the Book called, <hi>The old Tenures;</hi> and another commonly called <hi>Littleton</hi>'s <hi>Tenures.</hi> This Book ſerveth for an Introduction to the young Students in the Common-law of <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>Juſtinian</hi>'s Inſtitutions doth for the beginners in the Civill-law. Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> did likewiſe draw certain Rules and Caſes of ſome Titles of the Common law into a method, but not of equall, or like, authoritie with <hi>Littleton</hi>'s. It is alledged by <hi>Ploden,</hi> in his Epiſtle, that in antient time, (as he had upon credit heard) there were four Reporters of our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <note place="margin">Reporters of the Law in former times au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized 2nd allowed by the King.</note> of Law which were chief men, and had a yearly Stipend for their travell therein paid by the Kings of this Realm, and they conferred to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at the making and ſetting forth of the Reports. It were to be wiſhed that there were the like courſe ſtill continued, and allowance
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:53249:48"/> given: So ſhould we not have been bereaved of ſo many worthy and unrecoverable Caſes and Judgments which are wanting, and no doubt either periſhed, or buried in ſilence, by which means the Students are deprived of the Lights and Helps which they might have thereby.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Eſtates allowed by the Law of</hi> England.</head>
               <p>HAving ſaid ſomewhat of the Grounds of our Common-law of <hi>England,</hi> it ſhould ſeem proper in the next place, to ſhew the Eſtates which the Common-law doth allow. And that briefly; for neither my Judgment in the Laws nor this place will fitly allow ſuch aperfect and exact Diſcourſe as may paſs without exception of the Learned in our Laws, or fully ſatisfie ſuch as are well experienced in the ſame. Onely that which ſhall be ſaid is rather ſet down as a general view, to conſider the ſtate and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:53249:49"/> courſe of our Laws; than as a plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form and preciſe inſtruction thereof.</p>
               <p>The Eſtates moſt abſolute which <note place="margin">Fee-ſimple of two ſorts.</note> the law doth allow, are either Fee-ſimple abſolute of Land to a man and to his heirs and aſſignes for ever: <note place="margin">Eſtate of Fee-ſimple conditional now made an Eſtate in Fee-taile.</note> or Fee-ſimple conditional, that is, to him and the heires of his body gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral or ſpecial, as it was at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-law which is accompted Fee-taile to his Heirs males or females, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the particular limitation.</p>
               <p>This Eſtate of Fee-ſimple abſolute <note place="margin">How times have altered the ſtate of Fee-ſimple.</note> and general is as ancient as our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-law, and perchance before the uſe of our Common-laws as they are now in ure; for from the beginning there was giving and granting of Lands, though not altogether in that exact and expreſs form which later times have required: becauſe at the firſt if one man had given Lands to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> another for ever, this had been held a ſufficient grant to him, and to his heires. But now the law hath ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and diſtinguiſhed, that if the word [Heirs] be not in the grant, it is no Fee-ſimple, but an eſtate for life. The eſtate in Fee-ſimple donditional <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:53249:49"/> was likewiſe (for the general pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice thereof) introduced upon later conſiderations, of which at the firſt there was no recovery left in the Giver, nor remainder could be limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted over (but after iſſue had, which was the condition annexed) the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nee, or he to whom the Gift was made, had power to aliene the whole Land and Eſtate.</p>
               <p>But afterwards this Eſtate in Fee-ſimple <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> conditional was in the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth year of King <hi>Edw.</hi> the firſt by a Statute made an Eſtate in tayle in the Donee, and a Reverſion in the Donor or giver. And then the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nee might not by any Act barr his iſſues, neither by forfeiture of offence, as Treaſon, nor by conveiance, though never ſo ſtrong, as Fine, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee how the greateſt and moſt beneficial Eſtate of Fee-ſimple, which the Common-law doth admit, hath received his degrees, his limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and alteration according as time, increaſe of knowledg in the Laws, and of Conveyances and Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances amongſt men have thought it meet: the like alterations we may
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:53249:50"/> finde in other Eſtates of leaſt extent, and benefit in the Laws.</p>
               <p>Where mention was firſt made of the ſtate of Fee-ſimple to be very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, though not always in one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe form; It is true, with a ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral reſpect of times in antiquitie. For among the <hi>Saxons</hi> Fee-ſimple was, <note place="margin">Fee-ſimple in uſe in the <hi>Saxons</hi> time.</note> and that by the name of Land to a man and his heires, as it appeareth in the <hi>Saxon Laws</hi> of <hi>Alfred,</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>qui terram habuerit per ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae ſeriem</hi> (the Saxon word is <hi>boc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande) ſibi relictam ab haeredibus ad alios alienandi poteſtas ei non eſto, ſiquidem praeſentibus cognatis coram rege aut e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopo ſcriptura aut teſtimonio poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, omni alienatione &amp; interdixiſſe il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum qui prius conceſſit, talemque ei impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſſe legem cum primo dederit:</hi> out of which may be noted, both the Fee-ſimple abſolute and conditional were then allowed, and in uſe. And alſo <note place="margin">Fee-ſimple conditional alſo known in the <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> time.</note> a man may ſee that in antient time how a gift to a man and his heires and a gift to a man for ever were all one. For when Erle <hi>Godwine</hi> came to the Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> to get the mannor of <hi>Boſeham</hi> in <hi>Suſſex;</hi> he
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:53249:50"/> firſt jeſtingly ſaid to him (as Mr. <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> ſaith out of <hi>Mapaeus) Da mihi Boſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi> The Biſhop (as it ſhould ſeem, ſcarcely knowing his meaning) an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him, <hi>Do tibi Boſeham:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon without any more livery, the Erle took and had poſſeſſion thereof to him and to his heirs; by which alſo we may ſee two things, that the word <hi>heirs,</hi> was not then of abſolute neceſſitie in a grant to create a Fee-ſimple, and that then ſuch ſtrict words and forms of Conveyances were not required, as of later times, to paſſe Eſtates of Lands.</p>
               <p>There are other Eſtates of inferior degree and dignity allowed by the Common-law; whereof ſome are accompted Inheritances and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold; Others but uncertain, and not for a prefixed ſeaſon or term.</p>
               <p>Of the firſt ſort is an Eſtate for life, <note place="margin">Eſtates for life two-fold.</note> and that two-fold, either created by the party, as by Leaſe, &amp;c. or elſe created by the Law, as Tenant by the Curtefie of <hi>England,</hi> (by having iſſue of a wife Inheritrix;) or elſe an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in Dower limited to a wife in mariage, and this reckoned Free-hold,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:53249:51"/> for that it is an Eſtate for life.</p>
               <p>An Eſtate for years by grant of the <note place="margin">Eſtates for years by grant.</note> partie, is, when by Leaſe either in writing or word, called a Leaſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rol, or by Will, ſuch an Eſtate is granted.</p>
               <p>An Eſtate for years by Law is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, <note place="margin">Eſtates for years by the Law.</note> as that which the Lord or <hi>Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> hath till his Ward be of full age: the like by <hi>Elegit</hi> grounded upon a Statute <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. upon a recovery of <hi>Debt, Treſpaſſe</hi> or <hi>Acknowledgment</hi> of Debt in the Chancerie or before a Judge.</p>
               <p>The like Eſtate for years by Law, is by the <hi>Statute merchant</hi> or <hi>ſtaple.</hi> By acknowledging a debt before the Major of the <hi>Staple</hi> of antient <hi>Cities</hi> and ſome ſpecial merchandizing Towns.</p>
               <p>The two laſt Eſtates for years cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated by the Law were ordained for the better recovery and aſſurance of due debts; but whether they, or that of a Guardian, be Eſtates for lives by Law ſome make queſtion.</p>
               <p>There are two other Eſtates where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <note place="margin">Tenant by Copie of Court-roll firſt reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Tenants at will: But now not ſo.</note> the Holders are called Tenans at Will; but of them (although they be ſo termed) the firſt is now allowed
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:53249:51"/> for a more ample Eſtate, by uſe and <hi>Continuance,</hi> that is to ſay, Tenant by Copie of Court-roll, firſt called, <hi>Tenant in Vilainage.</hi> But now according to the Cuſtome of <hi>Mannors,</hi> theſe Tenants are not to be altered, but may renew their Eſtates by common courſe.</p>
               <p>The other, which is the laſt, the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tenant at will</hi> the meaneſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate the Law allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of.</note> leaſt and meaneſt Eſtate that the Law alloweth, is called, <hi>Tenant at will,</hi> who hath no longer term than ſtandeth with the will and pleaſure of the <hi>Landlord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of Aſſurances and Conveyances which grow out of theſe Eſtates by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-law.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SInce we ſee that the Eſtates and Intereſts of Men cannot paſs from one unto another, but by Deſcent or by Conveyance; It were not amiſs to manifeſt the general courſe of Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances which are uſual, and admitted by the Common-laws of this Realm. Theſe Eſtates have for the moſt part their paſſages by <hi>Feoffment,</hi> by <hi>Deed,</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:53249:52"/> by <hi>Fine</hi> and <hi>Releaſe,</hi> by <hi>Common-reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very,</hi> by <hi>Wills</hi> and by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Feoffment</hi> is by <hi>Liverie</hi> and <hi>Seiſin,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Feoffment.</note> that is, by deliverie of Poſſeſſion upon the Land, by taking of <hi>turfe and twigg</hi> (but in antient time, as <hi>Bracton lib.</hi> 2. <note place="margin">How it was executed in antient time.</note> ſheweth, when there was no Houſe on the Land, it was heretofore <hi>per fuſtim &amp; per baculum;)</hi> and this <hi>Livery,</hi> by <hi>Bracton,</hi> is called, <hi>Veſtimentum do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationis,</hi> thereby putting the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to whom the Eſtate is granted in poſſeſſion, or ſome other to his uſe by Letter of <hi>Attorney.</hi> And though this be of the Poſſeſſion only; yet without <hi>Liverie</hi> and <hi>Seiſin</hi> no <hi>Feoffment</hi> can receive life or force.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Feoffment</hi> is proper to an Eſtate <note place="margin">A <hi>Feoffment</hi> proper to an Eſtate for life at the leaſt.</note> for life at the leaſt, and ſo upwards, or elſe by grant of the Reverſion and Attornament of the particular Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which muſt be by Deed: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the poſſeſſion paſſeth not by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery only. This Conveyance was antient and moſt of Force, being noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, of which the Country might take notice, and is much uſed at this day.</p>
               <p>Exchange of Land whereby one <note place="margin">Exchang of lands.</note>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:53249:52"/> parcel of Land is exchanged for an other of equall eſtate, heretofore much uſed but not now.</p>
               <p>Grants by Deeds written in paper <note place="margin">Graunts by Deeds with <hi>Dedi &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſi</hi>
                  </note> or parchment ſealed and delivered with theſe words, <hi>Dedi &amp; conceſſi, &amp;c.</hi> have been antient and moſt uſual, ſo is it yet uſed; but not ſo frequent, eſpecially in Eſtates of any value.</p>
               <p>An other Aſſurance there is by Fine, which alſo is antient: at the firſt it was the agreement of parties upon <hi>Arbitrement</hi> or otherwiſe after a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie ariſen, when an Action is brought and hanging, for ſo is the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Law after <hi>H.</hi> 3. his time, for before, and then, Fines were received of many ſuch things and in ſuch ſort as will not be now admitted. So was it ſet down betwixt them in theſe words; <hi>Haec eſt finalis concordia,</hi> that is, That this is the final agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ſuch and ſuch perſons. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as ſome ſay, it was called, <hi>finis, quia finem imponit litibus,</hi> becauſe it maketh an end of ſtrife. This Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance is moſt antient, as ſome hold it, before the <hi>Conqueſt;</hi> but now uſed in the King's Court of <hi>Common pleas,</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:53249:53"/> and principally in ſome Courts of <hi>Record,</hi> to make the Aſſurance more forcible and certain.</p>
               <p>The ſame by a Statute made in the <note place="margin">Fines ſtrengthned by Statute.</note> 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year of <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. was ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and by the ſame Statute every perſon of full age, of ſound minde, out of priſon, and within the Realm, were bound and concluded by a Fine, if they did not make Claim within a year and a day after the Fine levied. But this Statute being thought too pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and prejudicial to Mens rights was repelled by another Statute in the four and thirtieth year of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third: And then men were at liberty, as before, to make their Claim at any time.</p>
               <p>But afterwards this Satute of 34 <note place="margin">Former Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Fines repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</note> 
                  <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. was alſo repealed by a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute in the fourth year of King <hi>H.</hi> 7. and alſo by a Statute in the 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. Fines were made ſo ſtrong, that after the Fine ingroſſed, and Proclamation made, all perſons after 5 years Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim were bound, unleſs they were under age, lunatick, in priſon, or out of the Land at the time of the Fine levied.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:53249:53"/>
               <p>And by this Statute of 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. Tenant in tail may barr his iſſue, which before he could not, by reaſon the Statute of 13 <hi>Edwardi</hi> 1. provided he ſhould not binde him by any act.</p>
               <p>Another Conveyance there is now <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Common-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverie</hi> an Undoer of former Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyances.</note> much in uſe, yet not very antient, which may be called a <hi>Pick-lock</hi> or an Undoer of former Aſſurances: This is called a <hi>Common-recovery,</hi> and was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver uſed till about the 12 year of <hi>Ed.</hi> the 4. it is not warranted by any Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, but an Invention firſt grounded upon a mere Conceipt, now held the ſtrongeſt Conveyance.</p>
               <p>The Invention was, that the Iſſue <note place="margin">The frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of <hi>Common-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries.</hi>
                  </note> in tail, or he in the Reverſion or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder upon a tail ſhould be barred of his Right and Eſtate by a recovery againſt the Tenant in tail: wherein Tenant in tail upon a ſuppoſed War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantie did vouch an eſtranger, becauſe the Iſſue or he in the Reverſion by this voucher was ſuppoſed to have a recompence in ſatisfaction of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, which being not ſo indeed, this is then but a mere Colluſion, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the moſt injurious Conveyance that the Law doth allow of to cut
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:53249:54"/> off mens titles and poſſibilities with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their privitie or ſatisfaction. This Conveyance is uſed only to cut off the Reverſion or Remainder de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon an Eſtate-tayle, and to deſtroy <hi>perpetuities</hi> which no other Conveyance doth, as a Fine is uſed to barr eſtrangers that pretend right of Poſſeſſion or Action, which no other Conveyance can doe.</p>
               <p>Conveyance of Land by Will or <note place="margin">Conveyance of Land by Will, how it ſtood at firſt.</note> laſt Teſtament in antient time was only in ſuch antient <hi>Cities</hi> and <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs</hi> which ſpecially preſcribed for the ſame, and that the Lands were deviſable by Cuſtome. But the greateſt part of the Land within this Realm was not ſubject to this kind of Conveyance, unleſs the ſame Land were firſt granted over to Uſes or in Truſt; and then the ſaid Truſt was deviſable by Will, becauſe it was a matter in Conſcience; and a <hi>Subpoena</hi> in <hi>Chancery</hi> was the only remedy.</p>
               <p>But in the 27 year of King <hi>H.</hi> 8. all thoſe Uſes were transferred into Poſſeſſions; ſo that by means there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of no Land, by any means was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeable
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:53249:54"/> but Cuſtomary-lands untill the 32 and 34 years of King <hi>H.</hi> 8. when it was Enacted that all Lands <note place="margin">Farther li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berty grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey Lands by Will.</note> might be deviſed by Will, and if the ſame were held in Socage tenure, the whole paſſeth by Will. But if of the King in Chief or of a Subject by Knight-ſervice, two parts only do paſs by Will, and the King, or Lord, of whom it is holden, is to have a third part during the nonage of the Heir, and the Heir the ſaid third part afterwards.</p>
               <p>The Conveyance by Uſes was in <note place="margin">Conveyance by Uſes, when and how it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun.</note> antient time unknown, and began in the time of the Civil-warrs of <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. againſt the Barons, and of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> bred and begotten by fear; for the <hi>owners</hi> of Lands doubting leſt themſelves by partaking ſhould be attainted (and ſo their livings forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) did convey their Lands over to their Friends in truſt, but received the profits themſelves: which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception or propertie by Law was called Uſe. And the party who was Owner in Conſcience was called <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuy a que uſe,</hi> or <hi>pernor</hi> of the profits. Alſo afterwards Uſes were invented
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:53249:55"/> by fraud to deceive Creditors of their Debts, Purchaſers of their Bargains, and Men that had right of their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; all which was remedied by the Statute of the 27 of <hi>H.</hi> 8. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Poſſeſſion of the parties truſted was transferred to the <hi>Ceſtuy a que uſe,</hi> and the Uſe and Poſſeſſion were incorporated and united. But yet at this day Conveyance by Uſe is very common, and many kindes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyances are lately ſprung up out of this Statute of 27 of <hi>H.</hi> 8. as Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gains and Sales for money. But this muſt be enrolled within ſix monthes by the Statute of 27 <hi>H.</hi> 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:53249:55"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of Actions and of their Trials ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Common-laws of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</head>
               <p>IT is a ſaying both in the Civil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laws and Common-laws of this Kingdome, that Actions whereupon the Trials of Suits betwixt party and party do depend, are of three ſorts; either <hi>real, perſonal,</hi> or <hi>mixt.</hi> The <note place="margin">Actions of 3 ſorts.</note> firſt concerneth the Title of man's Lands and Freeholds; the ſecond of their Goods and Chattells; and the third are in <hi>Rem &amp; perſonam ſimul,</hi> as Waſte, <hi>Quare impedit, Ejectione,</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>Actions heretofore uſed for real <note place="margin">Actions real.</note> matters were Aſſiſes, Writts of Entry and Writts of Right for Fee-ſimple, and as ſome hold for Fee-tail, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Precedents of experience, alſo Formedon for Fee-taile, <hi>Cui in vita,</hi> for a Woman upon the diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of her Inheritance by her husband.</p>
               <p>And for perſonal Matters and <note place="margin">Actions per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal.</note>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:53249:56"/> Contracts it was, as at this day: which real Actions were ſo uſed, becauſe the partie oftentimes was barred of his Entry by a diſcent, that if one did diſſeiſe or unlawfully diſpoſſeſs an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of any Land, and the Diſſeiſor or Wrong-doer died thereof ſeiſed, the lawfull Heir, or he that had the Right, might not put the other out of poſſeſſion or enter for his Right, but ought to ſue firſt for it.</p>
               <p>But by the Statute of 32 of <hi>H.</hi> 8. <note place="margin">The moſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Trial of Actions real at this day.</note> no diſcent to take away an Entry may be without five years peaceable poſſeſſion. And therefore now to bring ſuch Titles to trial, the uſe is either to enter and bring an Action of treſpaſs, and thereby to try the Title, or to diſtrein ſome Cattel upon the ground, and upon a Replevin to avow a dammage Feſant, that by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the Cattell hath treſpaſſed his ground, the intereſt thereof may thereby be tryed; but the common courſe is to ſeale a Leaſe upon the Land, and ſo to try it by an Action of <hi>Ejectione firmae.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Few real A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions now uſed, being full of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay.</note>
               </p>
               <p>At this day few real Actions are uſed, becauſe they are more full of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:53249:56"/> delay, and alſo they are more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory and binding againſt the party: for a former Recovery was a good Plea, but in theſe perſonal Actions it is not, for in them the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may bring as many Actions as his purſe will maintain.</p>
               <p>Alſo Actions upon the Caſe for <note place="margin">Actions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Caſe are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</note> Words are very common.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:53249:57"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of Trials allowed by the Laws of</hi> England.</head>
               <p>AS it is uſual amongſt men to commence Suits and Actions, ſo it is of neceſſity that ſome certain Form ſhould be preſcribed, by which thoſe Variances, Suits and Actions ſhould be brought to Concluſion: ſo hath the Laws of this Land, and Wiſdome of the Law-makers, found out two wayes for the Trial of Suits, <note place="margin">Two ways for the Trial of Suits and Variances.</note> which is either by Jury upon the Oaths and Verdict of twelve Free-holders, or elſe by Battaile between the parties (but this is out of uſe) or their Champions, or by the Oath of the defendant which is called, Ley Gager.</p>
               <p>Some have conceitedly ſaid, that <note place="margin">A conceited opinion of Trials.</note> the Trials (except Battaile) have confiſted upon the number of twelve with a triple diſtinction, as twelve Judges for matter in Law, twelve Jurors, and twelve in Wager of Law, for ſo is the form.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:53249:57"/>
               <p>There is a Trial alſo by the Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate <note place="margin">Trial by Certificate of the Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op, &amp;c.</note> of the Biſhop for Baſtardy and Mariage; alſo of Infancie, by Inſpection of the Court; alſo of Villanage, by his Kinsfolks; alſo Death of the Husband by proofs in Dower. But theſe (eſpecially the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of theſe) are not ſo much in uſe though allowed by our Laws.</p>
               <p>Of which Trials, although Trial by <note place="margin">Trial by Battaile not aboliſhed, nor lately uſed.</note> Battaile being antiently uſed, and is not yet aboliſhed by any Statute, yet by reaſon of the unchriſtian and bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy proceedings thereof, (when the ſtrongeſt Hand and Heart may over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the beſt Right, and loſſe of Living is determined with loſſe of Life,) it is therefore obſoleted, and grown out of uſe. Such Trial by Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile was appointed to be in Tuttle-Field in the 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> where the Champions, Liſts, Judges, and all being prepared, the Demandant was non-ſuite, and ſo that Trial cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: And another was appointed in the ſame place about the 8 of King <hi>Charles</hi> 1. but it was taken up and ſo ended. This Trial was both in civil and criminal Pleas. In civil Pleas
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:53249:58"/> it was only in a Writt of right by Champions; in criminal Pleas it was in an appeal of Death by the parties.</p>
               <p>Battaile is alſo termed a Trial in <note place="margin">A Trial ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Battail but by Writ.</note> a Writ of right, of Advouſon and <hi>Rationabilibus diviſis,</hi> and other Writs which concern the Right only; as <hi>Fitz-herbert</hi> witneſſeth: and alſo in civil Cauſes the Defendant might ſometimes wage Battle himſelf, as <hi>Glanvil</hi> ſaith, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Trial by Oath is (as heretofore) <note place="margin">Trials by Oath.</note> uſed by wager of Law upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts without ſpecialtie in an Action of Debt.</p>
               <p>This trial about <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. and <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. time was uſed in Actions which began <hi>ex maleficio:</hi> as in contracts <hi>ex ſtipulatione;</hi> for in Treſpaſſes it hath been uſed, as divers authorities are in the Year-books: But yet of late by reaſon mens Conſciences were found to be large and foul, whereby the Oath of a perjured perſon for his owne profit might much prejudice an honeſt Man, the Trial by Oath is <note place="margin">Trial by Oath is much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</note> much prevented, by turning the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly uſed Action of Debt into an Action upon the Caſe, wherein no Wager of Law lyeth.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:53249:58"/>
               <p>The moſt common and proper <note place="margin">Trial by Jury moſt frequent and in force.</note> Tryal of Suits in this Kingdom (here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore and now in force) is by Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that is, by Oath and Verdict of twelve Freeholders, both in Actions reals for Lands, and Actions perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals for Contracts and Treſpaſſes. In this Trial, the Jury is not tied only to the Evidence of two men or of more Witneſſes, but may find <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem facti</hi> upon Circumſtances, or by Witneſſes, or ſometimes (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for want of manifeſt or probable Evidence) upon their own Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges: And in Caſes doubtfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning points of Law the Judges are to deliver <hi>Veritatem Juris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Jury erre in their Verdict, <note place="margin">Attaint of a Jury erring.</note> an Attaint lyeth againſt them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the matter muſt be tried by 24 ſufficient and ſubſtantial Jurors, and that to be final. If it be found by them that the former Jury hath given a falſe Verdict and were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworn, the party wronged is to be reſtored to his Right, and the firſt Jury grievouſly puniſhed by the Common-law, which puniſhment is mitigated by the Statute of 23 <hi>H.</hi> 8.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:53249:59"/>
               <p>If upon any Action or Suite com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced, <note place="margin">Error of Judgement how re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</note> the Judges do erre in Judgement in any Court of Record, or that the ſame be ſuppoſed; A Writt of Error lyeth before other Judges ſuperiors. If in the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, it lyeth in the Exchequer Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber by the Statute of 31 <hi>E.</hi> 3 Cap. 12. If in the Common-pleas or Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Latine proceedings it lyeth in the Kings-bench; If in the Kings<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bench, heretofore it lay only in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, but now by the Statute of 27 <hi>Eliz.</hi> in the Exchequer-chamber before the Juſtices of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas and Barons of the Exchequer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:53249:59"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of ſome things in the Miniſters and Proceedings of our Laws conceived worthy to be reformed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEcauſe there are divers who do complain much againſt our Laws, whereof I may be bold to ſay that many (if not the moſt part) do not rightly diſtinguiſh betwixt the Uſe and the Abuſe of our Laws, <note place="margin">The Uſe and Abuſe of our Laws not well di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by ſome.</note> or betwixt the Laws themſelves, and the ill Practice and Proceedings of ſome corrupt perſons in the handling and trial of them; and for that I have formerly made ſome Apologie for our Laws in anſwer of theſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations: I hold it as fit in plain and ſincere dealing to deliver what defects, or other indirect proceedings I do conceive there are practiſed in the Trials of Suits, tending to the delay, overburdening, and deluding of the Subjects in their Suits, or to the defrauding of the Law it ſelf <note place="margin">The Authors intention.</note> in the withdrawing or declining of it from its natural pure and upright
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:53249:60"/> Courſe: which I ſhall ſet down by way of ſuppoſition (only as farr as I can conceive) rather than of any peremptory poſition. And in the ſame ſence have I ſpoken all the reſt; allwayes ſubmitting the ſame unto deeper Judgement of them that are learned in our Laws.</p>
               <p>The Defects whereof I ſpake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Defects of 2 ſorts, that is in Trials &amp; Proceedings of the Law.</note> are of two ſorts, Defects in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, and Defects in the Proceedings of our Law. The firſt whereof, as I conceive, proceedeth ſpecially from two cauſes, want of underſtanding or indifferency in Jurors who trie, want of Integritie in Judges who direct Jurors much in matter of Fact and have the whole power in deciding points of Law.</p>
               <p>Touching the former, whereby in <note place="margin">Want of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in Jurors.</note> courſe the Verdict of Juries, the Rights, Inheritances, &amp; whole Eſtates of moſt of the Subjects within the Kingdome are either tryed or ſubject to be tryed; and yet in many places the Jurors (for the moſt part) are found to be ſimple, of mean capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, and of as ſmall ſubſtance in Eſtate: for either no better are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pannelled,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:53249:60"/> or if better be, they of beſt Abilitie and Judgement, do ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelves; preſuming that either by ſome excuſe made for them, or by ſome other means, they may be diſpenced withall, or, if this ſerve not, the worſt is but to pay ſome ſmall Fine: So uſually the Service is impoſed on them that are leaſt able to diſcharge it: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to the no ſmall prejudice of mens Rights; wherein it were to be wiſhed, that either by ſome farther Laws (or at the leaſt by better Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the former Laws) Sheriffs <note place="margin">Sheriffs to be compell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pannell able men in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> were compelled to impannell in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries none but men able for Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Subſtance; And, that ſuch being impannell'd, a more ſtrict <note place="margin">No diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with Jury men to be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> Courſe were taken by the Juſtices for their better appearance and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance without any kind of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation or connivence. Care hath been taken to remedie this by the Statute made 16 and 17 Car. 2. 3.</p>
               <p>Alſo another abuſe there is concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the impannelling of Jurors wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of reformation, which is, That the Jurors of the principal pannel
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:53249:61"/> ſeldome appearing full, it is found an uſual practice for the Plaintiff to requeſt Free-holders (his friends) to <note place="margin">Free-holders deſired to ſtand in view that they may be retorned of the Jury.</note> ſtand ready within view of the Court, to be put into the Tales; therefore to avoid this miſchief it were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to have a ſpecial Oath always adminiſtred unto the Jurors, thus added, That they are not requeſted by either partie or laboured by any for them. It ſhould ſeem that the like Oath were needfull to be given unto the Sheriff or ſome ſevere penaltie appointed againſt the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pannelling of Jurors at the nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the parties or their freinds, whereby many men have received great hurt and prejudice. Alſo it <note place="margin">The Sheriff and the Jury to have a more ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Oath.</note> may be held as requiſite that the Jurors had a more ſpecial and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Oath when they are ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and do appear (but before they are ſworn of the Jurie,) to know whether they have been foreſtalled by Informations or Perſuaſions, as well as that they will give their Verdict without any particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to either ſide; for it is like they will make more conſcience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:53249:61"/> examined upon their Oath before they come to the Trial than after, when they have ſuddenly ſwallowed the Oath without publick examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Juſtices upon Oath, or particular and private of their own Conſciences by this Oath: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there is good proviſion alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy taken by our Law, that exception and chalenge may be taken upon rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and juſt cauſes allowed by the Law, yet ſince this cannot be certainly known, who is laboured and dealt withall before-hand, but by the examination of a mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience upon a mans own Oath; I am perſwaded that this would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent many corruptions in Trials by Juries; whereunto the nature of man is ſubject to be drawn, by ſolicitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of friends, promiſe of reward, or fear of diſpleaſure. And it would take away the ſcandal layed upon the Trial of Juries, which as it is different from the courſe of other Laws, ſo being well looked to by theſe and the like cautions, there is no doubt but it is a moſt excellent kind of Trial, eſpecially in matters
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:53249:62"/> of Fact whereunto it is principally ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied; and being thus exactly execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I will be bold to ſay, that it excells the Trialls of all other Laws, and is one of the worthieſt parts of proceedings in our law, whatſoever ſome Calumniators have ſaid to the contrary, whereof he that ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be farther ſatisfied, may find it fully demonſtrated in that noble and learned Chancellor of <hi>England Forteſcue</hi> his Book.</p>
               <p>Touching the other point where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there may be ſome prejudice in <note place="margin">Touching the Judges ſinceritie.</note> the Trials of Suits for want of ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in the Judges, although there are at this time as reverend, upright, and learned Judges, as hath been at any time within this kingdome: yet that amongſt them, there have been always ſome who might be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times led by affection or by ſome other private reſpects, may not be denied: unleſs we ſhould think, that they all and every of them, had more priviledge of not crring, or of not affecting, liking or diſliking, than either any other Judges or men of any other profeſſion in the world
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:53249:62"/> are induced withall: Therefore as a great Prince was content (nay did command) that every day one ſhould come into his Chamber, and put him in mind of his eſtate, and to tell him theſe words: <hi>Remember that thou art a mortal Man.</hi> In like ſort it is a thing fit to be conſidered, whether it were not convenient, that the Judges every Term and at every Aſſiſe, or at <note place="margin">An addition to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Oath.</note> leaſt once every year, ſhould publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Court and in open audience of the people take an Oath, That they have not received, nor will receive any gift or reward, or promiſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, for their favour, in any Cauſe heard or to be heard before them; nor will for favour, fear, or affection, incline to either partie, otherwiſe than as the very truth of the matter ſhall move; nor ſhall receive private Information, Meſſages, or Letters of Recommendation to draw them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide from ſincerity, or to ſhew favour to any partie: but that they ſhall ſpeedily make known the ſame in open Court: By which means the Judges ſhall be leſs importuned by men of power, and ſhall keep their
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:53249:63"/> Conſciences clear, and unſpotted. If the like Oath were given to the <note place="margin">A means for the Judges to avoid im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie, &amp;c.</note> Maſters of the Chancery, who in ſome Caſes, and at ſome times, do ſit as Judges, and moſt commonly by their Reports do much guide and direct the Decrees in that Court; it might perchance avoid much imputation to themſelves and prejudice to others. But againſt this there is no doubt but there will be many Objections made. As firſt, That this Oath being new <note place="margin" type="runSum">Objections againſt giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Oath to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es.</note> and ſo often taken would argue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt in the uprightneſs of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and that it will be a diſgrace not only unto them but to the Place wherein they ſit, and conſequently an imputation to the Juſtices of the Realm; that they ſhould not be truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon an Oath, (as Chriſtians ought to be in other Caſes.) And next, that it will be an impeachment of reputation to all former Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Judges, who were not ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſo ſtrict a Band. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if this were now neceſſary, then were they in former times let goe with too long raines of libertie and of looſeneſs.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:53249:63"/>
               <p>That which may be anſwered to <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw. to theſe Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</note> theſe Objections is this: Firſt, That this new, more ſtrict and frequent Oath doth not ſo much argue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt in the Judges as put them in minde of their Duties; no more than the often calling of a Steward or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great Officer to a ſtrict and often Accompt doth preſuppoſe that his Faith is alwaies doubted; nay, it is the beſt means for his diſcharge (which moſt wiſe and honeſt men do much deſire:) and ſo in this Caſe it may be ſaid, that this Oath, thus taken, is the ſtrongeſt Argument that may be to free the Judges from ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of Corruption (whereto they may many times be ſubject cauſleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:) for what man of any charitable and reaſonable conſideration will conceive, but that he that is more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ſtrictly ſworn to doe his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will be more carefull to diſcharge it, than he who but once in his life re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth that Oath? And for ſome part of this Oath it is ſuch, that no Judges of this Land have been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſworn unto, and yet it is ſuch as, by the opinion of ſome both wiſe
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:53249:64"/> and learned, is held moſt neceſſary.</p>
               <p>For the other Objections: That it will be a diſgrace to their Places, and to precedent Judges, and Judgments, that theſe are oftner and more ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſworn than were former Judges. Divers do deem that neither of theſe conſequents will enſue. One reaſon is, That if this Oath be a diſgrace to precedent or to preſent Judges; then the like would enſue, That an Oath taken by a Biſhop of this Land (not long ſince) of his clearneſs from Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and from giving any thing for his Biſhoprick, would be a diſgrace to him or to his Predeceſſors, who had not taken the like Oath before. Yet I think no man will conclude ſo, but rather, that this is a worthie Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, fit to be followed and to be left unto poſterities. Alſo it may be ſaid, the more multiplicitie of Suits that doth increaſe (as indeed they doe dailie) the more caution is to be uſed, and the more care to be enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto the Judges in the Trial of them. Secondly, The former Judges followed the Oath which was given them, and therefore no diſgrace to
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:53249:64"/> them that their Succeſſors have a more ſtrict Oath; nor is it any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to them that receive it: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it belongs unto latter times, to provide for that which former Ages have left undone. And in this new Oath, no Judge is ſingled out, or made a mark by himſelf, which if he were, it might indeed tend much to his diſgrace, as a great argument of diſtruſt in him. But whether this Oath, or any part of it, and whether the latter, if not the former, be to be uſed, or whether it be often or ſeldom to be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred; is a matter which I ſubmit wholly to the Cenſure of ſuch as are moſt Judicial and fit in the higheſt ſeats of Authority and Judgement.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond Point, ſpoken of before, which concerneth the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burthening of the Subjects by delays and by diverting the right Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Law. This is not to be attributed to the Laws themſelves nor to the Judges thereof, but to the corrupt miniſters, officers, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitioners of the Law, who do (as moſt men in other Faculties are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed)
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:53249:65"/> prefer their own private profit before the publick utility: They from whom theſe faults do flow (which are commonly but not juſtly imputed to the Laws) are, amogſt others, theſe; that is to ſay, Councellors at Law, Atturneys, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in Courts of Records Sheriffs and their Bailiffes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For the firſt ſort, which are the Councellors at Law and Barriſters, as they are called, the right Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Law (in divers particular mens Caſes) in Suits, is many times diverted, and ſometimes overthrown by their multitude, inſufficiency, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of delatory, or defective Pleas, by their taking of exceſſive Fees, and by their abſenting of themſelves from the Barrs, and places appointed to plead for their Clients, after that they have taken Fees.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the multitude of Councellors <note place="margin">Multitude of Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors.</note> at Law and outer Barriſters is ſo great, that many of them are not able to maintain themſelves, and ſome have few or no Clients at all, eſpecially ſuch of the ſecond ſort as were named to be inſufficient, who
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:53249:65"/> if any Suitors at Law come unto them for Counſel by reaſon of their acquaintance, kindred, or other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate reſpects, they many times ſend them away unſatisfied, or if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on ſuch weak Councellors, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times their good Cauſes (for want of ſound Counſel) are overthrown. The reaſon of the multitude and inſufficiency of many of theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors <note place="margin">The Inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors at Law.</note> at Law (as I conceive it) is, becauſe divers of them are admitted to the Barr before they have read over half the Volumes of the Law, and before they have with any good Commendation or allowance, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the exerciſes at Mootes, and at Readings, which is requiſite for the place, and for the teſtimony of their Profeſſion and ſufficiency: but having lived ſo long in one of the Inns of Court, as is preſcribed by the orders of that houſe wherein they are; although they be (and are known to be) no profitable or painfull ſtudents: yet, by favour they find meanes to be called to the Barr, many times to their own hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance, and much to the hurt of ſuch
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:53249:66"/> as have their Counſell. The ſecond Cauſe of this their inſufficiency is, for that they have of late been permitted to plead at Barr, and to put their hands unto Pleadings, as ſoon as they are made Barriſters: whereas in former times it was neither uſual or allowed, that they ſhould either plead at Barr or put their hands to Pleadings till three years after they were called: and in thoſe times they were kept more hardly and ſtrictly to their Mootes and Pleadings in thoſe houſes wherein they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued. The Inconveniencie of this generall, untimely and promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous kinde of Pleading and counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by all ſorts of Lawyers in <hi>Rome</hi> (aſwell the unlearned as the able and ſufficient) was foreſeen and in ſome ſort prevented by <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the Emperor in his time, who ordained <note place="margin">Auguſtus his reſtraint of Lawyers in Rome.</note> that no Lawyer ſhould practiſe without his royal aſſent and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion firſt had. If the King's Majeſtie did take this courſe with our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lawyers, or elſe aſſigned ſome others of greateſt authoritie and Judgement in the Law to take
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:53249:66"/> good notice and aſſurance of their ſufficiency before they ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to practiſe, there would not be ſuch a deluge of inſufficient Councellors at Law within this Kingdome, by whoſe Ignorance and want of knowledge many mens Inheritances and Eſtates are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown.</p>
               <p>For their perillous advice of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lays, <note place="margin">The ill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Councellors given to their clients.</note> and of other evaſions to procure gain unto themſelves, and leſs unto others: it is ſure that there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Councellors at Law who ſtudy nothing more than (as it may be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly termed) the Gall of the Law; how to ſeek evaſions, and to defeat the true meaning of the Law, and aſwell to draw ſome into danger of the Law and to overthrow the Right of others by their own incircumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by their Adverſaries cunning, and by the advices of ſuch wicked Councellors againſt whom there ſhould be ſome ſharp Law made for their puniſhment: or if not ſo, yet it ſhould ſeem requiſite that every Councellor at the Law, ſhould <note place="margin">An Oath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be given unto Councellors at Law.</note> (when he is called to the barr) take
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:53249:67"/> ſome ſpecial Oath for his upright dealing in the advice of his Clients; to proceed according to Equity, and that he ſhould not lead them into any by paths of indirect and un-conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable evaſions, contrary to the true meaning and upright courſe of Law, and of a good Conſcience. By this means (if they who take this Oath have any good Conſcience in them) the expence of much money in Law may be ſaved, and honeſt peaceable men kept from the trouble of quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and unquiet Neighbors in Cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Suits.</p>
               <p>Another abuſe there is offered by <note place="margin">The exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Fees that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors take.</note> the Councellors at Law in the taking of exceſſive Fees, which late Cuſtome their extream covetouſneſs, and the neceſſities of mens Eſtates in their Suites have introduced: For of late years (and in the memory of many men yet living) <hi>xx s.</hi> was a good Fee for a great Councellor, not onely to move but to plead at the Barr; and if a Serjeant at Law had <hi>x s.</hi> for to argue a Caſe, he thought himſelf well rewarded. But now what Councellor of account and of good
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:53249:67"/> practice is there, that will think <hi>xl s.</hi> a ſufficient recompence if he do ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue any mans Caſe at the Barr? nay that Serjeant at Law who hath but <hi>v l.</hi> given for ſuch a purpoſe, will goe thither with an ill-will, or elſe not come at all; beſides how often <note place="margin">Many Fees every Term for one Cauſe.</note> they muſt be feed in one Caſe, even in one Term, although of the pooreſt Client they have, (if they have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to come often unto them) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon experience, and many poor mens Purſes, can too well tell. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when it pleaſed the King's Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty at his firſt coming to this Crown of <hi>England</hi> graciouſly to take notice of this enormity, and to make known his Pleaſure that indifferent and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Fees ſhould be taken by the Councellors at Law of their Clients, ſome of them did reſtore (or at leaſt offer to reſtore) part of the Fees pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered unto them, which continued no longer with any of them than the dread of puniſhment or of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger drew them thereto. But where it is alledged by ſome, that the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of all Councellors is not alike, <note place="margin">All Lawyers not of like ſufficiency or merit.</note> nor their pains and travell all alike,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:53249:68"/> and therefore their Recompence can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be equally meaſured, no more than in other Faculties can the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors thereof merit as much the one as the other.</p>
               <p>To this I think it may be eaſily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That although the ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and pains of every one be not anſwerable unto the beſt, yet there ſhould ſome proportion be limited, what the beſt might deſerve, and how much he ſhould take in ſuch <note place="margin">Some pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Fees to be limited.</note> and ſuch particular Caſes; by which alſo ſomewhat a correſpondent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence might be awarded to others of inferior degrees and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, though not to be ſcanted by the penny yet at the leaſt to be rated by the pound, whereby a man of reaſonable Eſtate (in a ſuite of reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable value) might compaſs his Right without his undoing: and although the Labourer be worthy of his hire, yet is it hard, that the Labourer for his hire ſhould have the value of the Land whereon he laboureth or more, as many Lawyers have.</p>
               <p>But chiefly divers of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors do offend and abuſe their
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:53249:68"/> Clients (ſometimes to their utter undoing) when ſome of them do take round Fees againſt a day of Hearing, and yet neither come to the place, or if they do they depart before it be heard, and ſometimes in the midſt of the Argument being ſent for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another Barr in another Cauſe, where perchance their Fee is greater or their Client of more reputation or nearer unto them, whereby men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on them according to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe after Fees taken, receive much prejudice, and ſometimes the ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their Eſtates. In this Caſe many men have much wiſhed that either they were enjoyned to plead at one Barr only, (according to anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent order, ſo ſhould they be certainly found, and their Clients not fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of their help) or elſe if that were not thought fit, yet that ſome ſevere puniſhment may be ordained and afflicted on ſuch Councellors as take Fees for ſeveral Courts in one day, and do break with their Clients.</p>
               <p>The 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> ſort of Miniſters towards <note place="margin">The Abuſe of Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</note> the Law, who do miſlead the people in their Suits, and ſometimes make
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:53249:69"/> them miſſpend their money in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking of unjuſt Suits, and ſetting on of men to cauſeleſs quarrels, (for their own private commodity,) are the Attorneys at Law, who do di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ways offend, and many of them offer much wrong. Firſt, for their <note place="margin">The Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tornies.</note> Multitude; for they have increaſed to ſuch a huge number of later years, that they cannot chuſe but make much work for the Lawyers and Law in the parts wherein they live; as in the Courts of Records at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter. Firſt, to begin with the Court of Common-pleas; Since this <note place="margin">Attornies of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-pleas.</note> Chief Juſtice of that Court came to his Place, he commanding an Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be made by Jury, of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and condition of Attornies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to that Court; it is ſaid that there were no leſs than 800. of them found already by Jury: ſo that the Complaint is common, that every Scrivener, and other mens Clerks, who have deſired that place, (paying a certain ſum,) have been all thereto admitted, to the no ſmall hurt of the Subjects of this Kingdom. But if the Lord chief Juſtice, who hath begun
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:53249:69"/> this laudable courſe, do perfect it, with out remiſſion, to weed out both the exceſſive ſurpluſage of their number, and diſcharge all them that are ill conditioned, or not of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent underſtanding and experience, (as no doubt but that there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of that ſort,) and no queſtion but he will doe it, (eſpecially if he be required thereto:) By this good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, other Courts of Juſtice may be purged of their ill members, to the generall good of the whole Realm.</p>
               <p>There is the like, though not ſo great an exceſſe of Attornies, in the <note place="margin">Attornies in the Kings bench.</note> Kings Bench at Weſtminſter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there are eſtimated to be about 200, and yet within the memory of ſome yet living, there were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove eight or twelve at the moſt; for indeed they ought not to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the Prignatories Clerks of that Court. But beſides theſe (who only make out Writts) there are nine parts of ten that are reckoned Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies <note place="margin">Attornies at large.</note> at large, as they call them, who neither take Oath, nor have any power to make out Writts, but yet every one of them keeps a Clerk,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:53249:70"/> and ſome two, to write under them, who muſt be maintained by their Maſters countenance, and ſometimes they maintain their Maſters, by bringing Cauſes, and Clients unto them: theſe ſwarming in ſo great numbers, cannot live, and grow rich (as many of them do) without they hearten and increaſe Suits and ſtirs betwixt their neighbours, which enormities might partly be reformed by the Statutes already made, if they were put in execution and by ſome other proviſion; for it ſhould ſeem <note place="margin">Proviſion made by former Laws againſt At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tornies.</note> that former times have had trial of their abuſes, and care to reform them, though there were not then ſuch urgent cauſe to take a ſharp courſe with them as at this inſtant.</p>
               <p>By the Statute of the 4 of <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. every Attornie ſhould be ſworn truly to ſerve in their Offices, but now no Oath at all given unto many of them, eſpecially to deal juſtly and uprightly, other than for the profit of their Court. By the ſame ſtatute, if any Attornie were openly found in default, by Record or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, he ſhould forſwear the Court,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:53249:70"/> and never after be allowed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute any Suite in any of the King's Courts.</p>
               <p>By a late Statute made 3 <hi>Jacobi nuper Regis Angliae</hi> none ſhould be henceforth admitted Attornies in any of the King's Courts of Record, but ſuch as have been brought up in the ſame Courts, or have been well practiſed in ſoliciting of Cauſes, and have been found of honeſt diſpoſition; which Statute (ſo well and lately made) is already ſet aſide, and grown out of uſe.</p>
               <p>By the ſame Statute no Attornie ſhall be allowed from his Client for any Fee or for any Disburſement in charge of Law without a ticket ſubſcribed with the hands of them to whom the ſame is given or paid, and ſhall give a bill, ſubſcribed with his hand, of all ſuch Charges concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid Suits. But yet we ſee this Law no ſooner made, but already altogether infringed by the Attornies and Solicitors: for it may be, that ſome of them do deliver a Bill of the Charges, but who is there that bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Ticket under the hands of
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:53249:71"/> the Councellors and Officers to whom the ſame is paid? This is an abuſe worthy to be reformed, and this Statute very neceſſary to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</p>
               <p>In the 33 year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 6. a Law was made that there ſhould be but ſix common Attornies in <hi>Norffolk,</hi> ſix in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> and two in <hi>Norwich.</hi> If then the Country were peſtered with Attornies, and that a Law muſt be made to aſcertain the <note place="margin">A Law al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made neceſſary to be executed for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Attornies.</note> number (which likewiſe ſhould be elected and admitted by the two chief Juſtices,) how much more need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is it now to have the like Law of reſtraint for all the Counties of this Kingdom, when we ſee how, even in thoſe Shires (then thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for) there are far greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Attornies, and ſuch for the moſt part as they are ſpecially noted (by them who know theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries) to be full of cunning, and many of them nouriſhers of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and contenders themſelves with their neighbours. Theſe being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the Conduits that convey Suits and Gain to covetous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:53249:71"/> men deſiring Law, with the loſſe and impoveriſhment of many: there is therefore great need that their numbers ſhould be leſſened, and their diſpoſitions, who ſhall be allowed to practiſe, well known to be good and honeſt.</p>
               <p>A third ſort there are of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of our Law which do offer oppreſſion and wrong unto the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this Kingdom in their Suits. And they are the Officers of the Courts of Records and their Clerks, <note place="margin">Abuſe of Officers and their Clerks in the Courts of Record.</note> whereof many do exact unreaſonable and unlimited Fees, not (or very ſeldome) vouchſafing to ſet down in a note under their hands what their Fees are, but demanding ſo much, or elſe nothing muſt be done, or if it be firſt done they will often detain it untill their own demands be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. So the Subject muſt give whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <note place="margin">No certainty of Fees in moſt Courts</note> it pleaſeth them to ask. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it hath been the hearty deſire of ſuch as wiſh well unto their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try (without any private reſpect unto themſelves) that there might be a certainty of Fees ſet down for every Court, and the ſame to remain in
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:53249:72"/> written Tables in open Court, ſubject to every mans view, whereby the Subjects who have Suits in Law may not have ſo great cauſe of loſs, and of complaint as now they have. Of the ſame nature (and indeed a part of this exaction) is the exceſſive <note place="margin">Exceſſive Rates for the writing of Copies.</note> Rates taken for writing the Copies of all Bills, and Anſwers, Replicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Rejoinders, and of all other Records within the Court of Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter and the Offices belonging to the ſame: Firſt for the foule and <note place="margin">Waſtfull Writing of purpoſe.</note> waſtfull Writing, next for the few numbers of Lines in every Sheet, and for the ſmallneſs of the Paper where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they write; they alwayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding ſo much for the ſheet, how few ſoever of lines, letters or ſyllables there be in the ſame; and allwayes they ſtrive to write the leaſt they can, with great letters, full of large daſhes, to make the more diſtance, and very ſpacious lines for their more Gain and the greater Charge of them who are forced to take out theſe Copies, whereby they raiſe great ſummes of mony out of the Subjects purſes, keep good houſes,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:53249:72"/> purchaſe much living, enrich them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and impoveriſh many Sutors at Law. If that ſome reaſonable ſtint of this Writing and the certainty of Fees withall might be ſet down and obſerved, it would without doubt yield great contentment, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit and eaſe unto the people of this Land, who, for the moſt part, feel, and ſome ſink under this burden.</p>
               <p>Beſides theſe before mentioned Abuſes in the Miniſters and Officers of our Law, there are ſome other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations and with-drawings from the right Proceeding of Law by ſuch as ſeek to pervert the ſame. As <note place="margin">The Judges ſelect cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, whom they hear moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and often.</note> firſt in every Court of Record in Weſtminſter, the Judges have certain ſelected men, on whom they are pleaſed to beſtow their favours, in yielding them ready hearing before others; which being perceived, they are the more reſorted to (and muſt have the more Fees.) This increaſeth the charge of the ſubjects, and yet many times diſappointeth them of their expectation. And although it be not unreaſonable that the Judge ſhould extend his favour more unto
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:53249:73"/> ſome than unto the reſt (by hearing them before others) yet conſidering the inconveniency of this favour, it were far better forborn, and to be ſome way elſe ſhewed unto them that deſerve it. There is alſo ſome <note place="margin">Rules of the Courts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain and unknown to the Judges.</note> defect in the Courts, concerning the Rules of the Courts, that ſometimes the Judges themſelves are ignorant of the Rules of their Courts, touching the times of Anſwer, Reply, Rejoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Imparlance, with the like cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, whereby they are forced to ask the opinions of the antient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and beſt experienced Attornies and Officers of the Court, touching thoſe Rules; where it were much better that time were taken by the Judges to examine theſe Rules, wherein perchance ſomewhat might be amended for the more ſpeedy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of Juſtice, and the ſame ſet down in writing might be more certain and ſubject to all mens knowledge, with leſſe hindrance to Suitors and to their Cauſes.</p>
               <p>There are alſo ſome Courts in Weſtminſter, where the Judges (as for example the Barons of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer)
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:53249:73"/> do alter upon new motions out of Court (as in the Chequer Chamber or in other places) the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <note place="margin">Alteration of Orders out of the Court.</note> made in Court. And that which was publickly ordered by all the Barons in open Court is often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed by one of the Barons; when either the plaintiff or defendant bringeth his Counſel, and upon ſome new information, getteth the former Order to be diſſolved, which tendeth much to the Trouble, Charge and Delay of many Suitors.</p>
               <p>In the Kings Bench and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where elſe (as it is ſaid) writing out of Record muſt be twice or thrice unneceſſarily copied, as upon a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition <note place="margin">Unneceſſary Copies to be taken out.</note> a copie of the Suggeſtion, then after Declaration, a new Copy, after iſſue or Demurrer, a third Copy; whereas each of them ſometimes coſt three, four or five pounds; and yet, with a little alteration, it is thought that one might ſerve for all.</p>
               <p>The incertainty and intricate am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguity <note place="margin">Incertainty and intrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</note> of Pleadings in the Courts of Records bring much dammage and danger unto the Subjects of this
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:53249:74"/> Kingdom, wherein many men (wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well unto our Laws) have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly deſired, That either ſome certain Formes of theſe Pleadings (if it were poſſible to be performed) might be drawn by expert men, and the ſame conſidered and corrected by the Judges, might ſtand for good: and thoſe Forms to be allowed as in <hi>Rome,</hi> at the firſt, the Forms of Actions were given to the Actors of the Law by the Pretors:</p>
               <p>Or if this may not be performed, <note place="margin">Advantages of pleadings not to be ſo penal.</note> yet that ſome other Courſe were taken upon the advantage of a Plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miſtaken than is in the Caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the King and his Subject.</p>
               <p>If alſo in Actions perſonal a ſhorter <note place="margin">A ſhorter courſe to be taken in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal.</note> and more certain Courſe were taken than is by our Common-law, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſomewhat hath been ſpoken before (as that which the Civil Law allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, or ſome other ſuch like) for ſpeedy and direct Trial without eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or circumvention; it would yield no ſmall profit unto the People that are forced to proſecute theſe Suits.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:53249:74"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>A <hi>Catalogue</hi> of ſome <hi>Law Books</hi> printed for, and ſold by, ſeveral Bookſellers in <hi>Fleetſtreet</hi> and <hi>Holborn.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1. <hi>Raſtell</hi>'s Entries, fol. price</cell>
                     <cell>3<hi rend="sup">li</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2. <hi>Pulton</hi>'s Statutes continued to the year 1670. price</cell>
                     <cell>50<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3. <hi>Cook</hi>'s Commentary on <hi>Littleton,</hi> price</cell>
                     <cell>18<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4. <hi>Dalton</hi>'s Office of Sheriffs with very large Additions, printed in the year 1670. fol.</cell>
                     <cell>12<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5. <hi>Townſend</hi>'s Tables to moſt of the printed precedents, Writs and Returns at Commom Law, fol.</cell>
                     <cell>12<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6. The Law of Common Aſſurances touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Deeds in General, viz. Feoffments, Gifts, Grants, Leaſes, with two Alphabetical Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, by <hi>W. Sheppard</hi> Esq; fol. price</cell>
                     <cell>14<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7. The Country Juſtice, containing the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Juſtices of the Peace as well in, as out of, Seſſions, and with Additions, by <hi>Michael Dalton,</hi> in fol. price.</cell>
                     <cell>8<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8. A Collection of all the Acts and Statutes made in the Raigns of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt and King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, fol. price.</cell>
                     <cell>14<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:53249:75"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9. Lord <hi>Cook</hi>'s eleven books of Reports in French, fol. printed 1672. price</cell>
                     <cell>3<hi rend="sup">li</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10. Lord <hi>Cook</hi>'s Book of Entries, fol. price</cell>
                     <cell>3<hi rend="sup">li</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11. Lord <hi>Hobart</hi>'s Reports with Additions, in fol. price</cell>
                     <cell>10<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12. Lord <hi>Dyer</hi>'s Reports with a new Table, fol. printed 1672. price</cell>
                     <cell>18<hi rend="sup">s.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>13. Compleat Clerk, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price</cell>
                     <cell>12<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14. An abridgement of all the Statutes in force and uſe from <hi>Magna Charta</hi> to the year 1670. by <hi>Edmond Wingate,</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price</cell>
                     <cell>6<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15. <hi>Fitz-herbert</hi>'s Natura Brevium Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and amended, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price</cell>
                     <cell>5<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16. Termes of the Law with Additions, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. printed in the year 1670. price</cell>
                     <cell>4<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>17. Doctor and Student, printed in 1673. price</cell>
                     <cell>2<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>18. The Compleat Juſtice in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price</cell>
                     <cell>2<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>19. <hi>Briddal</hi>'s view of the Laws of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price</cell>
                     <cell>1<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>20. <hi>Littleton</hi>'s Tenures French and Engliſh, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price</cell>
                     <cell>2<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. 6<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21. Lord <hi>Cook</hi>'s Compleat Coppyholder, with additions, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price</cell>
                     <cell>1<hi rend="sup">s.</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22. Abridgement of the ſtatutes that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the knowledge and practice of the Common-law in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price</cell>
                     <cell>1<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>23. Compleat Attorney, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price</cell>
                     <cell>3<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:53249:75"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>24. <hi>Forteſcue</hi> of the Laws of England, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price</cell>
                     <cell>3<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>25. <hi>Placitae Latinae Redivivae,</hi> with Additions, printed Mich. Term 1673. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price</cell>
                     <cell>6<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>26. The Tranſactions of the High Court of Chancery both by practice and precedent, with the Fees thereunto belonging in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. by <hi>Will. Tothill</hi> Esq; late one of the ſix Clerks, printed 1673. price</cell>
                     <cell>1<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. 6<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
